<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sō ̃ma thanatou, the body of death: or, a discourse concerning the saints failings &amp; infirmities Wherein this position, viz. that absolute freedome from sinne is not attainable in this life, is both proved and improved, in three sermons preached in St Edmunds church in the city of New-Sarum; the first upon Wednesday Novemb 24. 1658. being the weekly lecture day; the two last upon August 14, 1659. being the Lords day. By Joseph Swaffeild minister of the gospel at Odstocke in the county of Wilts.</title>
            <author>Swaffield, Joseph, ca. 1625-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2218:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sō ̃ma thanatou, the body of death: or, a discourse concerning the saints failings &amp; infirmities Wherein this position, viz. that absolute freedome from sinne is not attainable in this life, is both proved and improved, in three sermons preached in St Edmunds church in the city of New-Sarum; the first upon Wednesday Novemb 24. 1658. being the weekly lecture day; the two last upon August 14, 1659. being the Lords day. By Joseph Swaffeild minister of the gospel at Odstocke in the county of Wilts.</title>
                  <author>Swaffield, Joseph, ca. 1625-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 118, [2]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for Francis Tyton at the three Daggers in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a table of contents, marginal notes, and a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saints --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:1"/>
            <p>ΣΩΜΑ ΘΑΝΑΤΟγ, THE BODY of DEATH: Or, A DISCOURSE Concerning the SAINTS Failings &amp; Infirmities.</p>
            <p>Wherein this Poſition, <hi>viz. That abſolute freedome from ſinne is not attainable in this life,</hi> is both <hi>proved</hi> and <hi>improved,</hi> in three SERMONS preached in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Edmunds</hi> Church in the City of <hi>New-Sarum;</hi> The firſt upon Wedneſday <hi>Novemb</hi> 24. 1658. being the <hi>weekly Lecture day;</hi> The two laſt upon <hi>Auguſt</hi> 14. 1659. being the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH SWAFFEILD</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Odſtocke</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is not a juſt man upon the earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not.</hi>
                  <bibl>Eccleſ. <hi>7.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Quemlibet valdè juſtum diſcutias in hâc vitâ; quamvis jam ſit dignus juſti vocabulo, non eſt tamen ſinè peccato.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Aug. Tom. 9. Tract. 41. in Johan. p. 210. Froben. 1529.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton</hi> at the three Daggers in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:2"/>
            <p>DIGNISSIMO VIRO,<lb/> 
               <hi>JOHANNI B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LKELEY</hi>
               <lb/> ARMIGERO.<lb/> PIETATIS AC LITERARUM<lb/> FAUTORI<lb/> EMINENTISSIMO.<lb/> TRES HASCE CONSCIONES<lb/> QUALESCUNQUE<lb/> 
               <hi>SARISB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIAE</hi> NUPER HABITAS<lb/> NUNC<lb/> PUBLICI JURIS FACTAS<lb/> Tenue Quidem &amp; Perexiguum<lb/> Perpetuae Tamen Obſervantiae<lb/> TESTIMONIUM<lb/> PER QUAM HUMILITER<lb/> D. D. D.<lb/> J.S.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:3"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen theſe Sermons were firſt preached, I intended no further publication of them, than from the Pulpit; nor did I deſire to have them any otherwiſe imprinted, than upon the <hi>fleſhly Tables</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38098:4"/>of the <hi>hearts</hi> of thoſe, to whom they were delivered.</p>
            <p>The truth is, they had ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever ſeen the light, had I not been earneſtly ſollicited by ſome Chriſtian friends for Copies thereof; whoſe deſires, as I was not willing to deny, ſo I have not been able, through want of time, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto to fullfill. To ſpare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my pains in tranſcribing them, was one inducement, that moved me to communicate them in this way.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:4"/>
            <p>Moreover, having been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with much importunity preſſed by ſeverall Chriſtians, to publiſh ſome other Meditations, preached during the time of our late Diſtractions and Confuſions, which though they were then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable (and I hope) not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unprofitable, yet I hitherto judged it more convenient to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, than to publiſh; and at ſome time or other (if providence ſhould afford an opportunity) to gratifie thoſe my friends, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:38098:5"/>ſome other Meditations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, which might be of more generall uſe.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, I am conſcious of ſo many weakneſſes and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Work, that had it not been for the Reaſons above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, I had never expoſed it to publick view. And I have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to judged the publication hereof the leſs neceſſary, becauſe juſt at the time, while I was ſtudying theſe Sermons, after I had preached the firſt of them, I met
<pb facs="tcp:38098:5"/>with a printed Sermon of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> entituled, <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah's Abatement:</hi> or, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the Saints;</hi> preached at <hi>Chatham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> at the Funerall of Mr. <hi>Gualter Roſewell,</hi> late Miniſter there; in which Sermon, the ſame truth, that is here treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, is excellently handled, though in another manner and method.</p>
            <p>But, though I have upon that account hitherto for born the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication
<pb facs="tcp:38098:6"/>of theſe Notes; yet, being of late in ſome danger of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the place, where for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven years laſt paſt I have exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed my Miniſtry; and (although that danger be through the good hand of Gods providence, I hope, now over; yet) conſidering the weakneſs of my body, and my ſhort time of ſojourning here, I became the more inclinable hereunto; knowing, that this may preach to my people, when I cannot; yea, when I ſhall be no more. And I
<pb facs="tcp:38098:6"/>was the rather inclined unto it, becauſe although the Reverend Author before-mentioned, and my ſelf proſecute the ſame Truth, yet in a different method; and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious method of handling the ſame Truth, may render the repetition the leſs unpleaſing. I deny not, but here and there, in the two laſt Sermons, I have borrowed a noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him, as I have alſo done throughout the whole, from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other known and approved Authors; yet herein, I truſt; I
<pb facs="tcp:38098:7"/>have not wronged either him or them, having for the moſt part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored it to the right owner again in the Margin; and (I hope) I may without vanity affirm, that I have not only uſed, but in ſome meaſure improved ſuch borrowed notions.</p>
            <p>For the ſtyle, in which theſe Sermons were preached, and in which they are now publiſhed, I confeſs it is very plain. But I hope the Truth therein contained will not find the leſs acceptance for the
<pb facs="tcp:38098:7"/>plainneſs of its dreſs. I remember, it was St. <hi>Pauls</hi> glory, that he <hi>came not</hi> (to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) with excellency of ſpeech, or wiſdome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to them the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God: and his ſpeech and his preaching was not with inticeing words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<note place="margin">Salvian.</note> but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit and of power, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>2.1, 4.</hi> Miniſters ſhould ſpeak <hi>utilia
<pb facs="tcp:38098:8"/>potius quàm plauſibilia,</hi> rather ſuch things, <hi>as may profit,</hi> than ſuch as <hi>may pleaſe:</hi> and they ſhould follow St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> direction to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> to make choice not of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerta</hi> but <hi>fortia;</hi> and ſtudy ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>work upon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> than to <hi>tickle the fancies</hi> of their hearers: and that rule of the Apoſtle ſhould be much reſpected by them, <hi>Let all things be done to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:8"/>
            <p> This Diſcourſe therefore (ſuch as it is) is now tendred to thy view, and thou art deſired to peruſe it, and with thoſe nohle <hi>Bereans,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> to ſearch the Scriptures, whether theſe things are ſo.</hi> I am ſure, if the matter of it be the truth of God, how plain ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſtyle be, it is worthy of all acceptation for the Lords ſake. If the Lord would but make it inſtrumentall for the leaſt good to any one ſoul, I have
<pb facs="tcp:38098:9"/>my deſire. With him therefore I leave it, and unto him, and to his grace I commend thee, Chriſtian Reader, reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, in any Goſpel-ſervice J. Swaffeild.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. <hi>18. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:9"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Doct. <hi>THe beſt of men are not freed from ſin in this life, but that in many things they offend all.</hi> page 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Doctrine is proved by Scripture.</hi> p. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How beleevers are freed from ſin in this life,</hi> viz.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>In reſpect of its dominion.</hi> p. 6</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>In reſpect of its guilt.</hi> p. 7</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>In reſpect of its condemning power.</hi> p. 13</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How beleevers are not freed from ſin in this life.</hi> viz.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Not in reſpect of its inherence.</hi> p. 14</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Not in reſpect of its infectious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty.</hi> p. 16</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Not in reſpect of its ſeducing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving power.</hi> p. 18</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reaſons, why God hath not wholly freed his people from ſin in this life, but ſuffereth them to carry about with them the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of corruption unpurged out, while they abide in the fleſh.</hi> p. 19
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That the power of his grace might be the more perſpicuous in their perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:38098:10"/>
                     <item>2. <hi>That the people of God might have mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of humiliation.</hi> p. 20</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>That Saints might be brought into a love with, and deſire after that eſtate, wherein they ſhall be wholly freed from ſin.</hi> ib.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reaſons, why the Lord ſuffers this corruption of nature ſo farre to prevail even in godly men, as to lead them into the wayes of ſin; in ſo much that it is true even of the beſt of men, that in many things they offend all.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theſe Reaſons are of two ſorts,</hi> viz.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>Some reſpecting God and Chriſt.</hi> p. 22. viz.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>God permits it for the glory of his power and faithfullneſs.</hi> p. 22</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>God permits it for the glory of his juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> p. 23</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Other Reaſons reſpecting the Saints.</hi> p. 24. viz.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Such as fall; and they are two,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Gods permits it to preſerve them from, or to cure them of carnall confidence.</hi> 24</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>By this means God is ſometimes pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to weaken ſin, and to ſtrengthen grace in them.</hi> p. 25, 26</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:38098:10"/>
                     <item>2. <hi>Reaſons reſpecting thoſe that ſtand,</hi> viz.
<list>
                           <item>1. <hi>God would hereby commend his love to them in preſerving them, and givs them ſome taſt and comfortable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of his goodneſs in upholding them when others fall.</hi> p. 27</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>God would hereby quicken them to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> p. 28</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Queſt. <hi>What is the difference between the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the Saints, and the falls of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men?</hi> p. 28, 29</item>
               <item>Differ. 1. <hi>A godly man doth not make a trade of ſin.</hi> p. 30</item>
               <item>Differ. 2. <hi>A godly man doth not ſin with a full conſent of his will.</hi> p. 32, 33</item>
               <item>Differ. 3. <hi>A godly man doth not ſin with a full purpoſe of heart.</hi> p. 36</item>
               <item>Differ. 4. <hi>The falls of a gedly man do not ſpring from propenſions of nature, but from the ſtrength and violence of temptation.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>Differ. 5. <hi>A godly man cannot ſin with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, but ſin is a burden to him.</hi> p. 42</item>
               <item>Differ. 6. <hi>A godly man doth not perſevere in ſin.</hi> p. 44</item>
               <item>Uſe 1. <hi>Refutation; to give check to the errour
<pb facs="tcp:38098:11"/>of thoſe, that aſſert a poſsibility of an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and perfect freedom from ſin in this life.</hi> p. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This opinion is proved to be contrary,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>To the Scripture.</hi> p. 48, 49, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>To Experience.</hi> p. 54</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>To the nature of grace and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> p. 54, 55</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>To the plentifull ſuffrage of Antiquity, yea to the conceſsions of ſome of our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh adverſaries.</hi> p. 55, 56</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Uſe 2. <hi>Caution both to ſinners and Saints.</hi> 61 <hi>Caution to ſinners.</hi> viz.</item>
               <item>Caution 1. <hi>Let them take heed how they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden themſelves to ſin by the falls of Saints, which are recorded in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> p. 62
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>In ſo doing they wreſt and pervert the Scriptures to a quite contrary end, than ever the Holy Ghoſt intended them.</hi> ib. 63
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The ends why God hath permitted the falls of Saints to be recorded in Scripture.</hi> viz.</item>
                           <item>1. <hi>To preſerve others from fainting under the burden of their ſins.</hi> p. 63</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:38098:11"/>
                           <item>2. <hi>That their falls might be warnings to others, to preſerve them from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> ibid.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Sinners will ſee but little reaſon to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden themſelves in ſin, by the examples of the infirmities of Saints recorded in the Scripture, if they conſider, how deeply they have ſmarted for their ſins.</hi> p. 66</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The Scripture records other things of Saints more worthy of imitation, than their ſins.</hi> p. 69</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Caution 2. <hi>Let ſinners alſo take heed, how they inſult over the godly, becauſe of their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> p. 70
<list>
                     <item>2. <hi>The children of God are ſanctified but in part in this life.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>If ſinners did reflect upon themſelves, they would find more juſt cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves than them.</hi> p. 71</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>In judging the children of God they condemn themſelves.</hi> p. 72</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caution to Saints;</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Caution 1. <hi>Let them take heed and beware of pride.</hi> p. 73
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſins of Saints are</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:38098:12"/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Of the ſame nature with the ſins of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men.</hi> p. 75</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Of the ſame deſert with the ſins of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men.</hi> p. 76</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>In ſome reſpects more hainous than the ſins of wicked men.</hi> ib.
<list>
                                 <item>1. <hi>God is more diſhonoured by their ſins.</hi> ib.</item>
                                 <item>2. <hi>Religion ſuffereth more reproach by their ſins.</hi> p. 77</item>
                                 <item>3. <hi>There is more unkindneſs in their ſins.</hi> ib.</item>
                                 <item>4. <hi>There is more unfaithfullneſs in their ſins.</hi> p. 79</item>
                                 <item>5. <hi>Saints are advanced to a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſtate than others are.</hi> p. 80</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Caution 2. <hi>Let them that ſtand take heed lest they fall.</hi> p. 81
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Directions to preſerve Saints from falling.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Direct. 1. <hi>Let them be watchfull.</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>Direct. 2. <hi>Let them carefully ſhun the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſin.</hi> p. 84</item>
               <item>Direct. 3. <hi>Let them look well to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi> p. 88</item>
               <item>Direct. 4. <hi>Let them look well to their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> p. 90.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:38098:12"/>
               <item>Direct. 5. <hi>Obſerve the firſt riſings of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and reſiſt them.</hi> p. 92
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>It is to no purpoſe to fly.</hi> p. 93</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>It is to as little purpoſe to yeeld.</hi> p. 94</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>It is to as little purpoſe to compound.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>It is then the beſt way to make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> p. 95
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rules for reſiſting.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>1. <hi>Reſist ſpeedily.</hi> p. 95</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Reſiſt univerſally.</hi> p. 97</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Enter not into a parley or treaty with ſin.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Reſiſt in the ſtrength of Chriſt.</hi> ib.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Direct. 6. <hi>Poſſeſs your hearts alwayes with apprehenſions of Gods preſence.</hi> 98</item>
               <item>Direct. 7. <hi>Labour to poſſeſs your hearts always with the fear of God.</hi> p. 99</item>
               <item>Direct. 8. <hi>Look up to Jeſus Chriſt with faith flaming out in prayer.</hi> p. 100</item>
               <item>Uſe 3. <hi>Exhortation.</hi> p. 101
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Bleſs God that you are delivered from a ſinfull ſtate.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Admire the juſtifying grace of God by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> p. 102</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Bleſs God for eſtabliſhing grace.</hi> p. 104</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:38098:13"/>
                     <item>4. <hi>Bleſs God for any diſappointments in the way of ſin.</hi> p. 106</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Every day labour for further degrees of mortification.</hi> p. 108</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Uſe 4. <hi>Conſolation.</hi> ib.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Sin cannot ſeparate Saints from the love of God.</hi> p. 109</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>God taketh notice of and accepts that good which is in his Saints, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their ſins.</hi> p. 110, 111</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the High Prieſt of Saints, is now in Heaven at Gods right hand making interceſsion for them.</hi> p. 114</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>There is a time approaching, and not far off, when Beleevers ſhall be freed from the very being of ſin.</hi> p. 116</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38098:13"/>
            <head>THE Saints Failings AND INFIRMITIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>James. <hi>3.2. former part of the verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For in many things we offend all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the foregoing verſe the Apoſtle dehort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the beleiving Jewes, to whom he wrote this Epiſtle, from the ſin of proud and uncharitable cenſureing; <hi>My Brethern be not many maſters;</hi> where the word <hi>maſter</hi> is taken <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38098:14"/>for a <hi>ſupercilious reprover,</hi> for one that is gotten into the chair of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, whence he doeth <hi>pro imperio,</hi> Magiſterially enough inveigh againſt the practiſes of other men.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures on <hi>James</hi> 3.1. <hi>Vide eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> And this dehortation the Apoſtle enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth with a double argument; the firſt drawn <hi>à periculo,</hi> from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this ſin. <hi>Knowing that we ſhall receive the greater condemnation,</hi> verſe. 1. <hi>either here,</hi> from men; Or, (wich I ſuppoſe the Apoſtle doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intend) <hi>hereafter,</hi> from the Judg of all the earth. It will be juſt in God, to be ſevere to the failings of thoſe that are ſo ſharp in cenſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Brethrens infirmities; by judging others, they doe but paſſe ſentence upon themſelves, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their own doome.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument is laid down in my Text, and it is drawn <hi>à communj hominum fragilitate</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus ad loc.</note>, from that common frailty, which is incident to all men; <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> It is an unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, to deny our Brethren that tenderneſs, which we need
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38098:14"/>our ſelves; and to judg and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn others, for thoſe failings, from which the beſt of men are not free
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que facit, qui veniam quâ opus habet, alijs negat.</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. <hi>ad loc.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In many things we offend all. We]</hi> the Apoſtle doeth not except him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though he was an Apoſtle of ſingular holyneſs, and of ſuch exact ſtrictneſs, that he was therefore ſirnamed the juſt.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. Eccl. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Offend]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe, and noteth aſſiduity and frequency, as a learned writer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth upon the Text
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vult aſſiduita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp; frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificare.</hi> Eſtius <hi>ad loc.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not handle the words with relation to the percedent verſe, but conſider them as an intire propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and being ſo conſidered, they cleerly hold forth this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> The beſt of men are not ſo freed from ſin in this life, but that in many things they offend all.</q>
            <p>The Propoſition lyes clear in this Text; ſo that had I no other proof, the Text it ſelfe were ſufficient; but it is eaſy to multiply other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which hold forth the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38098:15"/>truth. I ſhall onely deſire you to read two or three Texts of Scripture, which give in evidence thereunto, and then I ſhall proceed.</p>
            <p>See what a challenge <hi>Solomon</hi> maketh to all the world, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Who can ſay I have made my heart clean; I am pure from ſin?</hi> Many indeed may ſay ſo <hi>boldly,</hi> but who can ſay ſo <hi>truly?</hi> The interrogation hath the force of an emphaticall negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So likewiſe, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.20. <hi>There is not a juſt man upon the earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not.</hi> I hope none will be ſo vain, as to except againſt theſe proofes, becauſe out of the Old Teſtament, ſeeing St. <hi>James</hi> in my Text, (which is a part of the New Teſtament) affirmeth as much. <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt you may think, that it was onely one Doctors opinion, you may ſee St. <hi>John,</hi> the beloved diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that <hi>leaned on Jeſus his breſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 13.23.</note>, he, in other words ſpeaketh the ſame thing. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay, that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38098:15"/>and the truth is not in us.</hi> And you have St. <hi>Paul</hi> bitterly complaining of that body of ſin and death, that he carried about with him, and ſhould carry about with him to his dying day, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. <hi>ad finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Point (you ſee) is cleer; in the proſecution of it I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this method,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew you, how beleevers are freed from ſin in this life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſhew you, how they are not freed from ſin in this life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall lay down the reaſon of the Doctrine, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall ſhew you, what is the difference between the Godly and the wicked in their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall apply the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>I beginne with the firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and ſhall ſhew you, <hi>how beleevers are freed from ſin in this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beleevers are freed from ſin in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38098:16"/>this life, in three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Quoad vim domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi</note> 
               <hi>In reſpect of the dominion</hi> of it. The great Apoſtle of the Gentiles expreſſely affirmes it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over you, for you are not under the Law, but under Grace.</hi> Sin indeed hath <hi>a being</hi> in beleevers, but it doth not <hi>reign</hi> in them, as formerly. Though ſin act the part of a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act the part of a <hi>King</hi> in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever; <hi>God ſending his ſon in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſin condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſin in the fleſh,</hi> Rom 8.3. Sin is condemned; it is dead <hi>judicially.</hi> It received its deaths blow in the death of Chriſt; though it lives, yet it raigneth not, it hath loſt its ſtrength, becauſe a beleever is not under the Law, which <hi>is the ſtrength of ſin</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56.</note>, but under Grace.</p>
            <p>Indeed its true, that, as it was ſaid of <hi>Carthage,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> was more troubled with it after it was ſubdued, than before
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plus Romae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotij fuit cum ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victâ Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagine quâm cum integrà</hi> Flor.</note>, by reaſon of frequent rebellions afterwards ſo a Godly man may be more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and vexed with ſin, when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38098:16"/>it is conquered, then he was while it raigned. But yet though it may be <hi>turbulent,</hi> it ſhall not be <hi>preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</hi> It was before a <hi>King,</hi> but now a <hi>Captive</hi> in him; before <hi>upon a throne,</hi> now <hi>in chains.</hi> Sin may moleſt and vex, even where it doth not raign. What is ſpoken <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12. in another caſe; As concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reſt of the beaſts, they had their dominion taken away, yet their lives were prolonged for a ſeaſon and time; We may ſay by way of alluſion concerning ſin; <hi>Its dominion is taken away, though its life be prolonged for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (my beloved) what a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is this, and what a mercy is it, that when others are under the command of every luſt, and led captive by every ſin, beleevers are freed from the commanding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſin? ſin doth not raigne in them for they are not under the Law but under Grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Quoad reatum</note> Beleevers are freed from ſin <hi>in respect of its guilt.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt hath freed them from the guilt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38098:17"/>of thoſe ſins, which otherwiſe would have ſunk their ſouls irrecoverably to the bottome of the nethermoſt hell; ſo that now there is no ſin can be charged upon beleevers account. Chriſt hath fully paid their debt of ſin, and therefore God cannot in juſtice require it of them. Had the guilt of any one ſin of beleevers been unſatisfied for, it would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Jeſus Chriſt under the power of the Grave. He could never have riſen from the dead, nor have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heaven, if he had not paid the uttermoſt farthing of that debt, which beleevers ſinnes had contracted. He hath ſo freed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers from the guilt of ſin, that their ſinnes ſhall never be charged upon them. <hi>The Lord hath laid upon him the iniquities</hi> of all beleevers, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.6. And they cannot be laid upon him, and upon beleevers too; but are in Gods account, as if they had never been committed, never to be laid to their charge more. Therefore it is called <hi>A taking away their iniquities.</hi> Hoſ. 14.2. And <hi>a take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38098:17"/>away the ſins of the world,</hi> Joh. 1.29. <hi>Behold the lamb of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</hi> And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is called <hi>a blotting out tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions;</hi> Eſa. 43.25. <hi>I even I am he, that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions;</hi> As a debt-book is croſſed, and the <hi>debt blotted out;</hi> ſo God <hi>blotteth out the ſinnes</hi> of his people, that they ſhall never be charged upon their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The promiſe is very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall; I will <hi>blot out</hi> thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. If a writing be but blur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little, and ſomewhat blotted, it may be read; but if it be <hi>blotted out,</hi> it is no more legible. But the ſinnes of Gods juſtified ones are not onely <hi>blotted,</hi> but <hi>blotted out,</hi> and that by God himſelf, who alone hath the power of life and death, of condeming and abſolving. Though an inferiour Officer ſhould blot out an inditement, that (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) may ſtand a malefactor in no ſteed; but when the King doth it, who is the cheife Judg, then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictement cannot returne. Now it is the Lord himſelf doth blot out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38098:18"/>ſin; <hi>I even I am he, that blottes out thy tranſgreſſion.</hi> Our ſinners are (as it were) fairly written, as an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and record againſt us, and our iniquities teſtify againſt us, till a pardon blotteth them out.</p>
            <p>Sometimes alſo it is called <hi>blotting them out as a cloud;</hi> Eſa. 44.22. <hi>I have blotted out as a thick cloud thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and as a cloud thy ſinnes.</hi> Our unpardoned iniquities, as a thick cloud eclipſe the light of Gods countenance from ſhineing upon us, till the beames of Gods free Grace and pordoning mercy ſcatter this cloud.</p>
            <p>Sometimes it is called <hi>a caſting them into the hottom of the ſea,</hi> where they ſhall be ſo buried as never to riſe againe, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Thou wilt caſt all their ſinnes into the depths of the ſea.</hi> If a thing were cavt into a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which might be fadomed, it might be brought up again; or if it were caſt upon the ſea onely, it might be diſcerned and taken up again; but when it is in the depth, caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depths, into the bottom of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38098:18"/>the ſea it cannot be fadomed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. By which Metaphore the Lord expreſſeth (as one obſerves
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Obadiah Sedgewick</hi> in his doubting Beleiver. p. 251.252.</note>) <hi>the powerfull energie of pardoning mercy,</hi> that ſinnes ſhall riſe no more againſt us. He will clear them ſo, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once forgiven, they ſhall come upon the account no more: He will drown their guilt, that it ſhall not come up againſt them before him the ſecond time. Some think that it is an alluſion to Gods great judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on <hi>Tharaoh,</hi> and the Aegyptian Hoſt, who when they purſued <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were drowned in the bottomof the red ſea
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Loves.</hi> Penitent pardoned. p. 44.</note>. God will deal with ſin as he dealt with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt. To ſhew how irrecoverably they periſhed, it is ſaid, <hi>they ſank as lead in the mighty waters,</hi> Exodus. 15.10. when God pardoneth ſin, ſin ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth like lead in the bottom of the ſea; the guilt thereof ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver riſe againſt a pardoned ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Sometimes it is called <hi>a covering ſin,</hi> Pſal. 32.1. <hi>Bleſsed is he whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, whoſe ſin is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38098:19"/>covered.</hi> Now you know <hi>quod tegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur non videtur</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eron. Si voluit segere, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit videre,</hi> &amp;c. Aug. in Pſa. 32.</note>, &amp;c. that which is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered is not ſeen, the glorious robe of Chriſt righteouſneſs <hi>covereth</hi> all the ſpots of Gods juſtified people, as a garment covereth all the moles and blemiſhes and imperfections in the body of man: ſo that the Lord <hi>ſeeth no iniquity in Jacob nor tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Iſrael.</hi> Numb. 23.21. The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which Text, is not, that there is no ſin in them, which God takes notice of; but that although God doe ſee ſin in them, with the eye of his knowledg and omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; yet he doth not ſee ſin in them with the eye of juſtice, ſo as to lay it to their charge. Their ſinnes are covered (ſaith one) <hi>Not ſimply and abſolutely, ſo as that God cannot ſee them; this would argue impotency and imperfection in God; but</hi> ſecundum quid, <hi>ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as that God will not impute them</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Newman</hi> in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the houſe of Comons Dec. 30. 1646. on <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. p. 21.</note>.</p>
            <p>And moreover, the Sctipture holds forth, that the ſinnes of Gods people are ſo putt away, that if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38098:19"/>God ſhould come afterwards and make inquiſition for ſin in them, it ſhall not be found; <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. <hi>In thoſe dayes and in that time ſaith the Lord; the iniquity of Iſrael ſhall be ſought for, and there ſhall be none; and the ſinnes of Judah, and they ſhall not be found.</hi> The meaning is not, that there can no ſins be found in the Saints; but that they ſhall not be found ſo, as to have the guilt of them charged upon them. Why, what hinders the finding of them? Or where ſhall they be hid? The laſt words of the verſe will tell you where they ſhall be hid <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>pardoning mercies of God: I the Lord will pardon thove whom I reſerve.</hi> The Lord will give ſuch a full and free pardon of ſin, that what ſearch and inquiry ſoever ſhould be made after it, there ſhoud not be ſo much as any ſcar or mark, not ſo much as any print or ſtain left, to be a witneſs of their ſin, or a plea for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Which leads me to the third particular</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Beleevers are freed from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38098:20"/>ſin <hi>in reſpect of the condemning power thereof:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quoad vim damnandi.</note> So that now <hi>ther is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8.1. Though there be <hi>matter of condemnation,</hi> yet their is not condemnation it ſelfe. Sin ſhall never bring thoſe under condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that have an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt; for that were derogatory to Gods juſtice, to receive full pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our debt at the hand of Chriſt, and yet to require it of us too. The great Judge of Heaven and earth will not doe ſo unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, as to expect that from us, which Chriſt hath paid for us to the uttermoſt farthing. Thus you have heard how beleevers are free from ſinn this life.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> My next work is to ſhew you <hi>how beleevers are not freed from ſin in this life?</hi> And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I ſhall lay open in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Non quoad actum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerendi.</note> Beleevers are not freed from ſin <hi>in reſpect of its inherence.</hi> Hence we read of the <hi>indwelling</hi> of ſin. <hi>It is no more I that do it, but ſin that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38098:20"/>dwelleth in me,</hi> Rom. 7.17, 20. Sin doth not onely <hi>lodge</hi> with us for a night, but it <hi>dwelleth</hi> in us like a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Tenant, that will keep poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion in deſpite of the owner, till the houſe be pulled down over his head
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Brinſly</hi> in his Treat. of miſticall Implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. p. 120.</note>. The beſt Saint alive is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Inmates. Though he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his ſins, yet his ſins will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him. Sin is by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Ivy in the wall
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ</hi> l. 2. H. 64. cited by Dr. <hi>Ed. Reynolds</hi> in his Treatiſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſinfullneſs of ſin.</note>. Though you cut off the body, and the ſtump, and the boughs, and the branches; yet the root remaining faſtened in the wall, it will ſprout out again, till the wall be pulled down. By o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it is compared to the fretting Leproſy ſpoken of <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.45. ſcrapeing will not ſerve the turn to remove it, but ſtill it ſpreads, till the houſe, the ſtones, and the timber thereof, &amp;c. be broken down
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ed. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds ubi ſupra.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in his Chriſtians Charter.</note>. Sin cleaves ſo faſt to our nature, that it will never totally and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally leave us, till theſe houſes of clay be demolliſhed. It ſticks as faſt to us, as blackneſs to an <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> all the water in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38098:21"/>cannot waſh it off. As long as there is wheat in the field, it will have chaff about it; as long as there is water in the ſea, it will retain its ſaltneſs; ſo ſin will cleave and adhere to us as long as we live. Hence the Apoſtle calleth it an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing ſin</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Heb. 12.1. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> rendereth the word <hi>Peccatum tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inherens</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Leigh Crit. Sac.</note>. A ſin that doth ſo tenaciouſly cleave to us, that it will not be ſhaken off. A man may as ſoon ſhake of his skinne from his back, as ſhake of this evill inhabitant. It will dwell in us, while we dwell in theſe Tabernacles of clay.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Non quoad vim infici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi.</note> Beleevers are not freed from ſin <hi>in reſpect of its infectious property:</hi> for it not onely cleaveth to our natures, but it defiles our beſt performances. Hence ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times duties are in Scripture called <hi>dung; Mal.</hi> 2.3. <hi>I will ſpread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your ſolemn feaſts,</hi> ſc. Becauſe of the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity that cleaveth to them. That the ſinnes of <hi>unregenerate</hi> men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with ſin is beyond diſpute;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38098:21"/>their beſt ſervices, as they come from them are ſinfull; for <hi>bad trees can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit.</hi> The queſtion is concerning the ſervices of <hi>regenerate</hi> men: And indeed it is a truth concerning the beſt works of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate men. Though they are not ſins, and hatefull to God (for to affirm ſo were to reproch the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and grace of Chriſt, by which they are wrought) yet this I dare boldly ſay, there is aboundance of iniquity cleaving even to their holy things, and to their beſt ſervices, that are done by the concurrence and contribution of their own faculties; inſomuch that did not Jeſus Chriſt their High Prieſt take away the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of their holy things, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume them with his ſweet odours, they would not find acceptance. Should God be ſevere to mark what is amiſſe in our beſt ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he would find enough in them to condemne us
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nullum unquam extitit pii hominis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus quod ſi ſevero Dei judicio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabile.</hi> Calv. <hi>Inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>§</hi> 11.</note>. For our righteouſneſſes are as filthy rags and as a menſtruous cloth. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 64.6.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38098:22"/>
            <p> Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Beleevers are not freed from ſin in this life,
<note place="margin">Non quoad vim ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi.</note> in reſpect of its ſeduceing and deceiveing power. It ſtill retaineth a power to ſeduce us, and draw us into ſinfull practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; in ſo much that too often it ſalleth out, that what we would and ſhould doe, we doe not, and what we neither would nor ſhould doe, that we doe
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.</note>; and when we would doe good, evill is preſent with us; and by this law in our members, which continually warreth againſt the law in our minds, we are too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten brought in captivity to the law of ſin; ſo that we have too often cauſe to cry out with the Apoſtle, <hi>Oh wretched man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> Rom. 7.23, 24. And thus I have alſo diſcovered to you <hi>how beleevers are freed from ſin in this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I proceed now in the third place (according to my propoſed method) to lay down the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the Doctrine; and they are of two ſorts.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſhall give you a few rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38098:22"/>why God hath not wholly freed his people from ſin in this life, but ſuffereth them to carry about with them the remainders of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption unpurged out, while they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I ſhall alſo lay down ſome reaſons, why the Lord ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth corruption ſo farre to prevail even in Godly men, as to lead them into the acts of ſin, inſomuch that it is true, even of the beſt men, that <hi>In many things they offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Why hath not God wholly freed his people from ſin in this life, but ſuffers them to carry about with them the remainders of corruption unpurged out, to their dying day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, it may be for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> That the power of his grace might be the more conſpicuous in their perſeverance. Hence it is apparent, that it is onely by grace, they have their <hi>ſtanding,</hi> as well as their <hi>being</hi> in grace; and that it is onely by the mighty power of God,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38098:23"/>that they are <hi>kept through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. It muſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully magnify the power of Gods grace, that a <hi>ſpark of grace</hi> ſhould be kept alive in the midſt of a <hi>ſea of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> That the people of God might have matter of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. God was pleaſed to ſuffer the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſs to be ſtung with fiery ſerpents and ſcorpions <hi>to humble</hi> them
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.15.16.</note>. So while we are in this world, God ſuffereth us to be ſtung with the fiery ſerpent of ſin, that we might be humble before him. <hi>Paul</hi> had a <hi>thorn in his fleſh, and a meſſenger of Sathan to buffet him, that he might not be exalted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.7. <hi>Beza</hi> thinketh that this <hi>thorn in the fleſh</hi> was inherent corruption
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam intelligit, quae teli in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar nobis inhaeret.</hi> Beza.</note>, and that it is call'd a <hi>meſſenger of Sathan,</hi> becauſe he doth kindle thoſe corruptions
<note n="y" place="margin">Qui illas cupiditates incendit. idem.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> That ſaints might be brought into a love with, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after that eſtate, where they ſhall be wholly freed from ſin. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God would have us to ſee the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38098:23"/>between a ſtate of grace and a ſtate of glory; and we ſhall by this meanes find heaven the more ſweet to us in the end, where we ſhall be beyond all poſſibility of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Our corruptions now, as the Children of <hi>Anak</hi> diſmay us; and as the <hi>Canaanites</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they are left for pricks in our ſides, and thornes in our eyes, that ſo we may the more long after that eſtate of glory, in which ſin ſhall be no more. And ſo I have done with the firſt ſort of Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I come now to give you an account, <hi>why the Lord ſuffers this corruption of nature ſo farre to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail even in Godly men, as to leade them into the wayes of ſin; inſomuch that it is true even of the beſt of men, that in many things they offend all.</hi> And the reaſons hereof are alſo of two ſorts; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, there are ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that <hi>reſpect God and Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, There are ſome that <hi>reſpect beleevers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with thoſe Reaſons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38098:24"/>that reſpect God and Chriſt, and they are theſe two <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, God permits it for the glory of his power and faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, For the glory of his juſtifying grace by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> God premits it <hi>for the glory of his power and faithfulneſſe.</hi> God turneth even the falls of his children to the uſes of his own glory. You will think it ſtrange, that even the falls of Saints ſhould conduce to Gods glory. Indeed they doe not <hi>per ſe,</hi> but <hi>per accidens.</hi> For ſin, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Gods children, doth exceedingly conduce to GOds diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour: (as I ſhall diſcover more at large, when I come to apply the point) but though in its own nature it redowneth to Gods diſhonour, yet through Gods wiſe ordering, it turneth to the uſes of his glory. For God is ſo good, that he would not ſuffer ſin, if he could not bring good out of it. It is the prerogative of God alone, who commanded light
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38098:24"/>to ſhine out of darkneſs to bring good out of evill. Now God ordereth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the falls of Saints to his own glory, even to the glory of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and faithfullneſs, in raiſing them after ſuch falls. To recover a fallen Saint out of the mire of ſin, is a worke of Gods almighty power; and as it conduceth to the glory of his power, ſo of his faithfullneſs too. For God hath promiſed, that although the righteous fall ſeven times a day, he ſhall riſe again. Now God ſometimes withdraws his <hi>manutenency,</hi> and takes off the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints of his grace, and permits Saints to fall into foul and hainous ſins, that ſo both his power and faithfullneſs may appear the more conſpicuous in raiſing them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> God permits it for the glory of his juſtifying grace by the righteouſenſs of Jeſus Chriſt. Free grace is exceedingly magnified in pardoning freely our manyfold ſins before converſion; but that after frequent falls we ſhould be ſet upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38098:25"/>our legs again, and that though we commit new ſins daily, yet there ſhould be new pardons iſſued out for thoſe new ſins; this doth exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly advance the riches of Gods grace in juſtifying us freely by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There are alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſons which reſpect the Saints, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>ſuch as fall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>ſuch as ſtand.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Reaſons which reſpect <hi>fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saints</hi> are theſe;</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> God permits it <hi>to preſerve them from, or to cure them of carnall conſidence.</hi> Chriſtians are too apt to think that they are rooted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that by their own ſtrength they ſtand: and therefore God is pleaſed ſometimes to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the ſupply of his ſpirit, and ſuffers them to fall, that he might keep them from overmuch confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the ſtrength of inherent grace. That was one reaſon (as I conceive) why the Lord ſuffered <hi>Peter</hi> to fall ſo fowlly, to take him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38098:25"/>off from carnall confidence. Who more cofident than <hi>Peter,</hi> when he profeſſed that though all men ſhould deny Chriſt, yet he would not? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.33. yea that he would rather dye with him, than deny him, <hi>verſe</hi> 35. yet becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> did not enough (if at all) renounce his own ſtrength, how ſadly did the Lord ſuffer him to fall, not onely to <hi>deny</hi> his Maſter but to <hi>forſwear</hi> him; and to his oath to adde a <hi>curſe and Imprecation,</hi> and <hi>damning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> (for ſo the notation of the Greek word imports) imprecating Gods wrath and <hi>eternall damnation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, if he knew the man
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caepit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrari, nempe ſe, h.e. corpus &amp; animam devovere aeterno ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itio.</hi> Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>ad loc.</hi>
               </note>? I doe not queſtion but that <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>reall,</hi> when he made the foregoing profeſſion to Chriſt, and that he did not onely <hi>complement</hi> with him, but that he <hi>really intended</hi> no leſſe, then his profeſſion held forth. But <hi>Peter</hi> failed in <hi>truſting too much to his own ſtrength,</hi> and therefore the Lord ſuffered him to fall, to take him off from ſuch carnall confidence
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtam paenam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſuae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidentiae.</hi> Pareus.</note>.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>By this meanes God is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38098:26"/>ſometimes pleaſed to weaken ſin, and to ſtrengthen grace in them.</hi> By Gods wiſe ordering and diſpoſeing of it, ſin loſeth ſtrength by the falls of Godly men. I confeſſe indeed, in wicked men ſin gets ſtrength by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very freſh act; the more a wicked man ſinneth, the more he would ſin; the more he ſinneth, the more he delights in ſin; the more he ſinneth, the more he is hardened in ſinne. But in the Godly, relapſes and falls into ſin, doe <hi>per accidens,</hi> through the wiſedome and goodneſs of God ſo ordering it, conduce to the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of ſin; for by this means there is wrought in them, ſtronger hatred againſt ſin, and deeper deteſtations of ſin; more experience of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of their own hearts, and more ſerious watchfullneſs, and greater fear, and more firm depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God, more renewed vowes and covenants and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt ſin. A man that climbes up a tree, if one foot ſlip, or a bough break, is the more carefull to take ſure footing afterwards; ſo the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38098:26"/>falls of a Saint make him take better heed to his ſteps, than he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. A leg once broken and well ſet again, is (they ſay) ſtronger than before. It is true in grace; grace groweth ſtronger after falls in the Saints; as we ſee in <hi>Peter,</hi> who though at firſt he was ſhaken by the breath of a maid, yet like a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar in Lebanon he grew ſo ſtrong afterwards, that the moſt violent winds of perſecution, yea death it ſelfe could not ſhake or overturn him.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God hath alſo ſome ends which reſpect</hi> thoſe that ſtand.</q>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>God would here commend his love to them in preſerving them,</hi> and give them ſome taſte and ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable experience of his goodneſs to them, in upholding them when others fall. This doth even fill their ſouls with an holy aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and admiration of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable goodneſs of God. <hi>Oh!</hi> (ſaith the ſoul now) <hi>Lord, others of ſtronger parts, and more eminent for grace,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38098:27"/>thou haſt ſuffered to fall</hi> foully, <hi>though not to</hi> fall away; <hi>Others, that were</hi> tall <hi>cedars in compariſon of me, thou haſt ſuffered to be greivouſly</hi> ſhaken, <hi>though not</hi> pluckt up <hi>by the</hi> roots; <hi>whence is it then that I a poor</hi> ſhrub <hi>am preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? how cometh it to paſſe that thou upholdeſt me?</hi> This wonderfully ſets off, and commends the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the love of God, and fills the ſoul with the admiration of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>God would hereby quicken them to prayer</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lapſus majorum, tremor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</note>: When a ſoul ſeeth others of ſtrong parts and eminent for grace to fall into any ſin, Oh! Then will the ſoul ply the throne of grace, and improve all his intereſt in God, and goe and beg of God the ſupply of his quickening ſpirit, that he may be thereby <hi>kept through faith unto ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much for the Reaſons of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>The next thing,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in proſecution of the Point, is to diſcover to you, <hi>what is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the infirmities of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38098:27"/>Saints, and the falls of wicked men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved, this is a weighty queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the cleer reſolution thereof may (through Gods bleſſing) be very conducible to your ſpirituall good and advantage; both for the preventing and removeing <hi>diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agements</hi> and <hi>imbondageing thoughts of fear,</hi> out of the hearts of weake Chriſtians; and alſo for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting and removing of <hi>carnall confidence,</hi> which may poſſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in the hearts of others, from what hath been delivered. For (my beloved) the ſins and the falls of Saints doe uſually very much diſturb the peace of their own conſciences; and they are as frequently a ſnare to carnall hearts to encourage them to ſin; and therefore it will be worth the while to reſolve this queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> What is the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the Godly and the wicked in their ſinning? between the infirmities of Saints and the falls of wicked men? Godly men ſin, and wicked men ſin; and yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38098:28"/>there is a vaſt diſparity and a many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold difference between the ſinning of the one and the other: and what that difference is I ſhall now diſcover to you.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>1</label> A Godly man <hi>doth not make a trade of ſin,</hi> he is not a cuſtomary ſinner. Though (poſſibly) he may ſometimes ſin over the ſame ſin, and renew the ſame tranſgreſſion; yet the ſoul putteh in its plea and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt it, as the Apoſtle doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. where he cryes out, <hi>Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from this body of death?</hi> It is here as in civill matters; if we make our <hi>challenge or demand,</hi> a cuſtome is at an end; though poſſib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch may be the power of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite party, that the acts may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed: So a Godly man <hi>putteth in his plea</hi> againſt ſin, and although (poſſibly) through his own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the violence of Sathans temptations, he may be once and againe <hi>overtaken</hi> with it, yet he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolveth againſt</hi> it, and <hi>prayes</hi> againſt it, and <hi>complaineth to</hi> God of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38098:28"/>ſtrength of his corruptions, and doth not <hi>allow</hi> himſelf in the leaſt ſin. <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, that <hi>he had choſen the way of truth,</hi> Pſal. 119.30. and yet he ſlipt with his tongue more than once; as when he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt, the King hath commanded me a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and he hath ſaid unto me, let not any man know any thing of the buſineſs whereabout I ſend thee, and what I have commanded thee; and I have appointed my ſervant to ſuch a place 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.2. and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters again with his tongue, and ſpeaketh either <hi>falſely</hi> or <hi>doubtfully,</hi> when the King of the Philiſtims ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him <hi>whether have ye made a rode to day? And David ſaid, Againſt the ſouth of Judah, and againſt the ſouth of the Jerahmeelites, and againſt the ſouth of the Kenites.</hi> 1 Sam. 27.10. When as his invaſion was againſt other countreyes, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs <hi>David</hi> did not make a <hi>trade</hi> of <hi>lying,</hi> for he had <hi>choſen the way of truth,</hi> Pſal. 119.30. and he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth afterwards in the ſame <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:38098:29"/>that <hi>he hated every falſe way, verſe</hi> 104. And this is the meaning of that place. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, doth not commit ſin</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, he doth not <hi>trade</hi> in ſin, and make it his <hi>work</hi> and his <hi>buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wicked men drive a <hi>trade</hi> of ſin; they <hi>deviſe, plot,</hi> and <hi>contrive</hi> ſin, which acts denominate them <hi>workers of iniquity.</hi> They are ſo far from putting in a <hi>plea againſt ſin,</hi> that they will (as I ſhall ſhew you afterwards) rather <hi>plead for</hi> their ſins, and they will labour more to <hi>make excuſes for</hi> them, than to <hi>get the conqueſt over</hi> them. They are ſo far from makeing preparation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the luſts of the fleſh, that they <hi>make proviſion for the fleſh to fullfill the luſt thereof,</hi> Rom. 13.14. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men by makeing a trade of ſin contract upon themſelves a kind of curſed neceſſity of ſinning. Sin by cuſtom becometh (as it were) another nature to them
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſutudo quaſi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda, &amp; quaſi affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricata natura.</hi> Aug. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de muſic.</hi>
               </note>, ſo that they can almoſt as ſoon ceaſe to be, as ceaſe to ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>A Godly man doth not ſin
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38098:29"/>with a full conſent of his will:</hi> he doth not yeeld a willing ſubjection to the commands of ſin. He doth not yeeld a <hi>ready and free obedience to it, as to a naturall Lord,</hi> but onely <hi>a forced</hi> and <hi>involuntary</hi> obedience, as to a tyrant. Sin cannot ſay of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, as the Centurion of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; <hi>I ſay to this man go and he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and to another come, and he cometh, and to my ſervant doe this, and doeth it,</hi> Mat. 8.9. For a Saints heart riſeth againſt the imperius commands of ſin; and the ſoul complaineth, and cryeth to God for helpe againſt it. A Godly man ſinneth with much reluctancy
<note n="e" place="margin">non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate plenâ ſed ſemiplenâ.</note>; his heart never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up heartly to the commands of ſin, but the evill <hi>which he would not doe, that be doeth,</hi> Rom. 7.19. There may be indeed a kind of <hi>negative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> in a Godly man, as to ſome <hi>particular acts</hi> of ſin, into which he may perhaps be carryed forth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>open</hi> reſiſtance; as when a thing is put to the queſtion, a man that is ſilent, may be ſaid to give ſome kind of conſent, when he doth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38098:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſuspend</hi> his own vote, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly declare his conſent, nor yet directly enter his diſſent. But yet (beloved) though a Godly man may be over-born ſometimes, and hurryed into ſome particular acts of ſin; yet he doth not directly or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminately conſent thereunto. It is the ſad complaint and the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full voice of grace, <hi>the evill, which I would not, that I doe. But I doe ſin, and I will ſin; I doe work iniquity, and I will work it;</hi> that's the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born voice of a ſinfull nature. Even then, when a Godly man, through violence of temptation, is drawn to the acting of ſin, yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in the will a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of oppoſition againſt it. As <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſtruggled together in <hi>Rebeccahs</hi> womb, ſo there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly a ſpirituall ſtruggling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twen the fleſh and the ſpirit in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving ſoul: <hi>The fleſh luſteth after the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh,</hi> Gal. 5.17, Now where there is this luſting and ſtruggling againſt corruption, there cannot be a full
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38098:30"/>conſent or compliance of the will with corruption. I told you before, that ſin acteth the part of a <hi>Tyrant</hi> in a Godly man. Now you know all the ſervice that is don to a Tyrant, is out of of violence, not out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. A Tyrant hath onely a <hi>coactive</hi> power over the <hi>perſons,</hi> but a King, beſides that hath a <hi>ſweet</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the <hi>wills and affections</hi> of his Subjects
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>His duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus differt justum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen à Tyrannide. Regi legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti libenter obediunt, quicquid praeceperit Tyranno inviti ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperant,</hi> &amp;c. Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>in Rom.</hi> 6.</note>, they love his <hi>perſon</hi> and delight in his <hi>ſervice,</hi> which rule, though it be not alwayes true in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill governments (for the unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs of ſome to obey their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne may ariſe from their own rebellion, and not from his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) yet it is moſt generall and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in the ſtate of ſin, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a King over rebellious ſubjects, who reject its yoke and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Sin may play the Tyrant, and uſe Saints like captives ſold under it, as <hi>Paul</hi> complaineth of himſelf, that he was ſold under ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. We read of <hi>Ahab,</hi> that he was ſold to ſin
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>King.</hi> 21.20.</note>, but in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſenſe. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſold himſelf, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38098:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:38098:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38098:32"/>became a voluntary in the ſervice of ſin. But <hi>Paul</hi> was ſold by <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Adam vendidit ſe primo, ac per hoc om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſemen ſubjectum eſt peccato.</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>in Rom.</hi>
               </note>, and from this captivity he could not utterly extricate himſelf, though he were (as one expreſſeth it) in bondage to ſin, <hi>as the creaturs are to vanity, not willingly but by reaſon of his act, that had ſubjected him long before</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ed. Reynoldes</hi> in his Treatiſe of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs of ſin.</note>.</p>
            <p>But now unregenerate men doe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obey ſins commands, they yeeld their members ſervants to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to iniquity unto iniquity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. They have no principle of grace within, to reſtrain them from ſin; but onely principles of rebellion, whereby they are impetuouſly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed forth into the wayes of ſin in a full career, or like a ſhip under ſail with a full wind.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>A Godly man doth not ſin with a full purpoſe of heart.</hi> When a Godly man ſinneth he is <hi>out of his road;</hi> for purpoſes are the road of our hearts, as cuſtome is of our lives. The honeſt traveller pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to keep on ſtraight to his journies end; and if he doe at any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38098:32"/>time miſtake his way, it is beſides his purpoſe. So—</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Peter denyed</hi> his Maſter, yet it was againſt the <hi>purpoſe</hi> of his heart, yea againſt the <hi>promiſe</hi> of his mouth. <hi>Judas betrayed</hi> his maſter, but he was <hi>reſolved</hi> before ſo to doe, as appeareth by his <hi>contract</hi> with the Scribes and Phariſees. As for <hi>Peter,</hi> he <hi>denyed</hi> his maſter, not becauſe he purpoſed to doe it; but becauſe he purpoſed not to doe it, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon Chriſt for ſtrength to preſerve him from the violence of ſuch a temptation
<note n="k" place="margin">A ſmall blaſt of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to overturn a man, who is puffed up with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of his own ſtrength; as here, the voice of a Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth <hi>Peter.</hi> Mr. <hi>David Dickson</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.69, 70.</note>. His fall indeed was dreadfull and terrible, but it was a <hi>ſudden ſurprize;</hi> the fixed purpoſe of his heart was againſt it.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible, that a Godly man may deliberate upon the committing of ſome ſin, when an occaſion is preſented; but I conceive, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a Godly man to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, how he may find out occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin. <hi>David,</hi> when he was upon the houſe top had an object preſented, but he did not goe up thither with an intention to ſeek
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38098:33"/>one. Godly men may be ſuddenly ſurprized, and be hurryed into the externall acts of thoſe ſin, which they never intended, and againſt which their purpoſes and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were moſt ſtrongly carryed forth.</p>
            <p>But now a wicked man ſinneth with full purpoſe of heart; he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and reſolveth to ſin, even then when he ſeemeth to pray and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt it. As <hi>Auguſtine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that before his converſion, when he prayed to the Lord to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify his corruption, he was afraid that the Lord would grant his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and mortify that luſt, which he rather deſired ſhould be ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>In exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eram à te caſtitatem &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ne cito ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audires &amp; ſanares me à morbo coucupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae, quam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleri male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam, quàm extingui.</hi> Aug.</note>. A wicked man ſinneth, and the purpoſes of his heart are that way, as thoſe whom the Prophet mentions, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 56.12. who ſaid <hi>Com ye, I will fetch wine, and we wil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abundant,</hi> q. d. We have been drunk to day, and we will be more drunk to morrow. And <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.21. <hi>Their heart walketh after the hear<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:38098:33"/>of their deteſtable things, and their abominations,</hi> i. e. The inclinations and reſolutions of their hearts goe or walk after their abominations.,</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>The falls of a Godly man doe not ſpring from propenſions of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but from the ſtrength and violence of temptation.</hi> That temptations are exceeding powerfull to hurry the beſt of men into ſin is evident, by that ſpeciall direction, that our Saviour giveth us to pray againſt temptation, and Gods ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to preſerve us therein. There is (ſaith a worthy Divine) a great difference, when a man ſinneth from his own habituated principles in wickedneſs, and from the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering force of ſome importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate temptations
<note n="m" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſs</hi> Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineing. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. par. p. 211.</note>. Such may be ſometimes the voiolence of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as that Godly men may be overborn therby, and hurryed in to thoſe ſins, which <hi>according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man</hi> they abhor, and hate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a <hi>perfect hatred. David</hi> profeſſeth, that he <hi>hated every falſe way,</hi> Pſal. 119.4. and yet (as you heard
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38098:34"/>before) he is over taken once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with that fault. A Godly man doth in his inner man <hi>delight in the Law of God,</hi> and hates thoſe ſins, into which he is drawn by the overpower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of temptation: his heart and thoſe ſinnes are upon tearmes of defiance.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the falls of unregenerate men proceed from propenſions of nature; nature is wholly ſet upon ſin. You need not drive a dog to his vomit, nor a ſow to the mire; it is naturall both to the one and the other. A naturall man (indeed) may be reſtrained for a while from his violent acting of his wonted impieties, (it may be) by reſtraining grace, or (perhaps) onely for fear of the Magiſtrate, or want of opportunity, or ſome ſuch occaſion or other, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene to hinder him from furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly running on to all exceſſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlyneſs; but there is ſtill in him ſuch a naturall propenſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to the wayes of ſin, that like water that hath been for a while bayed up; if once the banks be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38098:34"/>down, or the floudgates open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it ruſheth forth with the greater violence; ſo if once thoſe reſtraints by which formerly a wicked man hath been held in, be taken off, he will breake forth again with the greater violence into his former lewd and ungodly practiſe. A naturall man may not unfitly be compared to a Lyon or a Beare, that may be (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) for the preſent chained up to prevent his doing miſchief, but ſtill retaines his ravenous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hath a naturall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to doe miſchief: So the heart of a wicked man, if onely chained up by reſtraining grace, or fear of the Magiſtrate, and not changed by renewing and ſanctifying grace, if he can but get looſe from thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints, will ſoon return to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vomit, to his former lewdneſs and ungodlyneſs; for he hath a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall propenſion and inclination to ſin. A wicked man when he ſins, is like a <hi>fiſh in the water,</hi> in his proper e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement. The wayes of ſin are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per element (if I may ſo ſpeak) they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38098:35"/>are moſt agreeable to the nature of a wicked man.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>A Godly man cannot ſin with delight but ſin is a burden to him.</hi> Though a Godly man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, yet he <hi>hates the evill that he doth,</hi> Rom. 7.15. yea he hates it with a deadly and irreconcileable hatred; ſo much the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, which <hi>David</hi> uſeth in that place quoted before, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.104. I hate every falſe way
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>à radice</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Odio proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus fuit.</hi>
               </note>. A Godly man that hath learned that leſſon which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.9. to abhor that which is evill, where the originall word is very emphaticall, it ſignifies to hate a thing with vehemency, and to loath it as Hell it ſelf. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound word; the ſimple verb im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports extream deteſtation; the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication therefore is aggravated by the compoſition
<note n="o" place="margin">Leegb Crit. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra.</note>. Indeed ſin is a Godly mans affliction and not his pleaſure, as is evident by the Apoſtles bitter complaint, ſo frequently mentioned already, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Oh wretched man that I am,</hi> &amp;c. the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38098:35"/>word ſignifieth (as <hi>Beza</hi> notes) one that is <hi>aerumnoſis &amp; perpetuis pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſatigatus,</hi> wearyed with trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and continuall combates
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Componi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur â ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (<hi>per ſynco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>ſuffero &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>luctus.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted <hi>in Lexic. Theol.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith it is <hi>vox anhelantis</hi> the voice of one breathing and pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, deſiring to be delivered from this ſervitude.</p>
            <p>But now a wicked man ſinneth with delight. Hence they are ſaid to <hi>love evill more than good,</hi> Pſal. 52.3. to <hi>chuſe their own way, and their ſouls to delight in their abominations,</hi> Eſa. 66.3. and to <hi>have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.12. The comfort of their lives comes in by fulfilling their luſts; ſo that they are diſcontented, when their luſts are not ſatisfied. Witneſs <hi>Ahab,</hi> who was ſick till he got <hi>Naboths</hi> vienyard, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.5. and <hi>Amnon,</hi> till he could ſatify his luſt upon his ſiſter <hi>Tamar,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. Such is their delight in ſinning, that they are unwearyed therein. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> gives us a notable deſcription of their reſtleſſeneſs and unweary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in ſinning. <hi>They ſleep not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they have done miſchief; and their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38098:36"/>ſleep is taken away unleſs they cauſe ſome to fall,</hi> Rom. 4.14, 16.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Differ. </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>A Godly man doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in ſin. The juſt man falleth ſeven times a day, but he riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> Prov. 24.16. Hence it is, that the Scripture, as it records the <hi>falls</hi> of any of the people of God, ſo it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords their <hi>riſeing</hi> again, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords <hi>Davids</hi> adultery and murder, <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> pride, <hi>Peters</hi> denyall and the falls of the Saints, ſo it records al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the tears, and, the ſighs, the groans the meltings, the humiliations, and the repentance of thoſe precious Saints. In the 51. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> you may read of <hi>Davids</hi> repentance at large; and although <hi>Hezekiahs heart was lifted up,</hi> yet you may read that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah humbled himſelf for the pride of his heart,</hi> 2 Chro. 32.35, 36. <hi>Peter</hi> fell fearfully, but a look, a glance of love from Chriſt melted him into teares, <hi>he went forth and wept bitterly,</hi> Luk. 22.61. A look of mercy from Jeſus Chriſt broke <hi>Peters</hi> heart, and opened the floudgate of his eyes too. <hi>And the Lord turned and looked
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38098:36"/>upon Peter, and Peter went out and wept bitterly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wicked men <hi>perſiſt and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere</hi> in the wayes of ſin; inſomuch that neither judgments <hi>threatned,</hi> nor judgments <hi>inflicted</hi> can reclaim them. They ſin, and <hi>care</hi> not; they ſin, and <hi>fear</hi> not; they ſin and they <hi>will</hi> ſin, let God ſay, or doe what he will, to the contrary. As thoſe did, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Withhold thy foot from being unſhod, and thy throat from thriſt,</hi> i. e. Why will ye goe down to <hi>Egypt</hi> for help? you'le get nothing by it but bareneſs and thirſt: but they ſay, ſtrangers we have loved, and ſtrangers we will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, q.d. Say thou what thou wilt, we will take our own way and our own courſe. So <hi>Jer</hi> 44.16, 17. notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God had denounced dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full judgments againſt that people, and that in great variety too, <hi>viz.</hi> Sword, Famine, and Peſtilence, <hi>verſe</hi> 11.12, 13. yet they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to goe on in their Idolatrous practiſes; they anſwered <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaying, <hi>As for the word that thou haſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38098:37"/>ſpoken to us in the name of the Lord, we will not hearken unto thee; but we will certainly doe, whatſoever thing goeth forth of our own mouth, to burn incenſe to the Queen of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Their wills were <hi>fully ſet</hi> upon their ſinfull wayes, let God ſay or doe what he would to the contrary. Thus alſo did the old world, though God ſtirred up <hi>Noah</hi> a <hi>preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to warn them for an hundered &amp; twenty yeares together; yet they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in their own wayes, and gave themſelves, to eating and drinking and ranne on to all exceſſe of riot, <hi>till the flood came and ſwept them all away,</hi> Matth. 24.38, 39. So <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> the Lord ſend <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> unto him ten times, and inflicted upon him ten plagues, one upon the neck of another; yet <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was hardened in the wayes of ſin. So true is that of the wiſe man <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.22. <hi>Though thou ſhouldeſt bray a fool in a morter among wheat with a peſtell, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the Doctrinall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38098:37"/>part, I proceed now to application, and this Doctrine may be improved ſeverall wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> This point gives us a check to the errour of thoſe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Refuta. </seg>
               </label> who aſſert a poſſibility of an abſolut and perfect freedom from ſin in this life. Such were of old the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> and the <hi>Cathari,</hi> who held that they could not ſo much as ſin in thought
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rogers.</hi> on the articles of the Church of England. p. 64.</note>. Such were the <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the <hi>Familiſts</hi> who imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves ſo free from ſin, that they needed not to pray <hi>Forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi> Yea even in our dayes this errour is revived again, and therefore it will not be unſeaſonable to ſpeak ſomething for your eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment in the truth, and whereby you may be antidoted againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of this poyſonous opinion. And all, that I ſhall ſpeak upon this Doctrine ſhall be by way of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. How contrary this opinion is to the Scriptures.</item>
               <item>2. How contrary it is to the experience of Saints.</item>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38098:38"/>
               <item>3. How contrary it is to the nature of grace and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <item>4. How contrary to the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſuffrage of antiquiy, yea to the conceſſions of ſome of our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh adverſaries.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I ſhall give you ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It is contrary to ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as doe cleerly aſſert what my Doctrine holdeth forth, <hi>viz.</hi> That the beſt of men are not ſo freed from ſin in this life, but that in many things they offend all. Diverſe Scriptures were alledged for the proof of the Doctrine, that doe cleerly aſſert this truth. To thoſe which were then mentioned, I ſhall onely adde, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. where it is expreſly affirmed, <hi>that ther is no man that ſinneth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is contrary to ſuch Scriptures, where the people of God. in their petititions and ſupplications, doe neceſſarily inferre this truth, that there is ſin remaining in them.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38098:38"/>Otherwiſe how can they pray as <hi>David</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1, 2, 9? <hi>Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy loving kindneſſe, according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy tender mercies, blot out my tranſgreſſions. Waſh me throughly from mine iniquity, and cleanſe me from my ſins. Hide thy face from my ſinnes, and blot out all mine iniquities;</hi> and as our Saviour teacheth his diſciples <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Forgiue us our debts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is contrary to thoſe Scriptures, where Chriſt is ſaid to be an <hi>Advocate,</hi> and an <hi>High Prieſt, to make interceſſion for beleevers, viz.</hi> 1 John 2.1. <hi>If any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>He ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them.</hi> Now, this were altogether needleſſe, if they had no ſin in them. If beleevers have no cauſes to plead, what need have they to have an advocate continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Court? If the Saints were free from ſinning, what need had they of an High Prieſt to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38098:39"/>for them? So that this errour deſtroyes the interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> It is contrary to thoſe Scriptures, that note the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, even of thoſe, whom the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in other Scriptures hath ſtiled <hi>perfect. Noah</hi> is ſtiled <hi>a juſt man, and perfect,</hi> Gen. 6.9. and yet afterwards you may read that <hi>Noah planted a vineyard, and drank of the wine, and was drunken and uncovered in his tent,</hi> Gen. 9.20, 21.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Abraham, the father of the faitfull,</hi> to whom God ſaid, <hi>walk before me, and be thou perfect,</hi> Gen. 17.1. was not without his <hi>imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections:</hi> for he fell twice into the ſame ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> of denying his wife, for which he was reproved by two Heathen Kings, <hi>viz. Pharoch</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar. Gen.</hi> 12, 12.13, 18, 19. &amp; 20.2, 9.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe <hi>David</hi> was by Gods own teſtimony <hi>a man after Gods own heart,</hi> Act. 13.22. which amounts
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38098:39"/>to as much as a perfect man, and yet it is well known, he was not without ſin; witneſs his adultery with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and his murder of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and his pride in numbring the people, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. &amp; 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> alſo is ſtiled <hi>a perfect man, Job</hi> 1.1. and yet ſubject to infirmities, as apeareth by his <hi>curſing his day,</hi> chap. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſa</hi> is ſtiled <hi>a perfect man,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. <hi>the heart of Aſa was perfect all his dayes;</hi> and yet in the very next chapter you have no leſſe than four ſeverall ſins of his upon record, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, His ſeeking to <hi>Benhadad</hi> King of <hi>Syria</hi> for aid againſt <hi>Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.23. Secondly, His impriſoning <hi>Hanany</hi> the Lords Prophet, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved him for his ſin <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10. Thirdly, His oppreſſing his ſubjects <hi>verſe</hi> 10. Laſtly, His ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Phyſicians, and not the Lord in the time his ſickneſs, <hi>verſe</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is ſaid to <hi>have walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before God in truth and with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart,</hi> 2 King. 20.3. and yet, when once God left him a little, to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38098:40"/>try what was in him, how doth he diſcover his imperfections? His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude is recorded 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.25. <hi>Hezekiah rendred not again according to the benefit done unto him.</hi> And his pride is alſo noted in the ſame <hi>verſe, but his heart was lift up;</hi> as alſo <hi>Eſay</hi> 39.2. where he too vainglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſhewed his treaſures to the Embaſſadors of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for which God threatneth, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in his ſons daies brought the Captivity.</p>
            <p>I'le give you but one inſtance more, and that is recorded <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. <hi>Zacharias</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and to have walked in all the Commandements of God blameleſſe;</hi> and yet afterwards he is ſtruck dumb for his unbelief, <hi>verſe</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Now if abſolute perfection and freedome from ſin were attainable in this life, queſtionleſſe ſome of theſe eminent ſervants of God would have attained it; which none of them ever did: for you have heard how the holy Ghoſt impeacheth them all of humane
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38098:40"/>frailties and infirmities.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It is contrary to ſuch Scriptures, where the repentance, and humiliation, and the Godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of Saints is recorded. <hi>Davids</hi> repentance is ſet down at large, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. and <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> repentance is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.26. <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, humbled himſelf for the pride of his heart;</hi> and <hi>Jobs</hi> repentance is ſet down, <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. <hi>I abhor my ſelfe, and repent in duſt and aſhes:</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> repentance is mentioned in no leſſe than three of the Evangeliſts, <hi>viz. Matth.</hi> 26.75. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.61, 62. So that the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous nature of this opinion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in nothing more, than in this, that it taketh away all grounds of humiliation and repentance and Godly ſorrow for ſin, in thoſe that beleeve. For he that ſaith there is no ſin in Saints, doth in effect ſay, that there is no need of repentance in Saints This errour (you ſee) eateth into the very vitals of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs; it overthroweth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; therefore beware of it, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38098:41"/>thus I have ſhewed you how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary this errour is to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is contrary to the experience of beleevers, who have felt, and bewailed corruption in themſelves even till death, and have acknowledged the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man, and have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed all thoughts of their own perfection in this life; as <hi>Joh</hi> did when he ſaith, <hi>If I juſtify my ſelfe mine own mouth ſhall condemne me, If I ſay I am perfect, it ſhall alſo prove me perverſe,</hi> Job 9.20. And <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 130.3. <hi>If thou, Lord, ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt marke iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> at large, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. <hi>ad finem.</hi> complaineth bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that ſinfull corruption, that did cleave cloſe unto him, and hang faſt upon him, and would doe to his dying day. The boſome-expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of all Saints, is enough to confute this vaine and fond conceit of perfection in this life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it is contrary to the nature of grace and ſanctification,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38098:41"/>which in this life (at the beſt) is but imperfect. The beſt Saints have a <hi>fleſh</hi> in them, as well as a <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and the one luſteth againſt the other, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. they have two men in them, an <hi>Old</hi> as well as a <hi>New;</hi> and the one muſt be <hi>put off,</hi> the other <hi>put on</hi> daily, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. and the doing of both is a worke of time, even of their whole lives. They have <hi>two lawes</hi> in them, one <hi>in their members,</hi> rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the other, which is in <hi>their minds, Rom.</hi> 7.23. inſomuch that though grace raigne in them while they live, yet corruption pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth often, and will dwell in them till they dye, <hi>verſe</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is contrary to the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſuffrage of antiquity, yea to the conceſſions of ſome of our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh adverſaries.</p>
            <p>For Antiquity take the Judgement of three or four for all. <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith expreſſely, <hi>None can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, as long as he is clothed with fleſh</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licto poteſt, quamdiu indumento carnis one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus eſt.</hi> Lactant. <hi>de vero caltu lib.</hi> 6. c. 13.</note>. Bleſſed <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo, that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious confeſſor, and famous Martyr
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38098:42"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes confeſſe our ſelves to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for whoſoever ſhall ſay, that he is without ſin is either a proude man or a fool</hi>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Semper debemus nos confiteri peccatores, nam quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſe im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maculatum. &amp; ſine pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato diceret, aut ſuperbus eſt, aut ſtultus.</hi> Cyprian.</note>. And <hi>who doubteth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>that concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence may be leſſened in this life; but not conſumed</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam quis ambigat, in hac vitâ poſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui, nou poſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumt?</hi> Aug.</note>? And <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, that the fleſh is <hi>Hoſtis, quem nec fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere poſſumus, nec fugare; an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which we can neither flee, nor yet put to flight.</hi> And elſewhere, ſpeaking concerning the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of ſinne, he ſaith, <hi>whether thou wilt or no, this Jebuſite will dwell in thy borders; it may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, but not utterly rooted out</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Velis nolis, intra fincs tuos habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeus; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, exterminari non poteſt.</hi> Bernard.</note>. And the maſter of the ſentences acknowledgeth, that <hi>we are not ſo redeemed from it, that it ſhould not have a being in us, but onely that it ſhould not reigne in us</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ab eà ſic re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempti ſumus, at non ſit, ſed ut non dominetur,</hi> Mag. <hi>ſent l.</hi> 3. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 19.</note>. And <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan</hi> another learned Papiſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth, that <hi>ſinne is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not extinguiſhed</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dumnatum eſt peccatum, non extinctum.</hi> Caſetan.</note> And <hi>Eſtius</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38098:42"/>another Popiſh author (howſoever he endeavour in other places to blanch thematter) yet in his Commentary upon thoſe words of the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Let not ſin reign in your mortall bodyes; that ye ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof,</hi> (upon thoſe words I ſay) he hath this note, <hi>The Apoſtle doth not ſay, let not ſin</hi> be, <hi>but let it not</hi> reign, <hi>&amp;c. becauſe as long as we are in this mortall body, ſin is in us, and cannot be rooted out of us during this life</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non dicit Apoſtolus, non ſit, ſed non regnet peccatum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>quia quamdiu ſumus in hoc mortali corpore, eſt in nobis peccatum, neque duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hâc vita extirpari poteſt.</hi> Eſtius <hi>in Ep. ad Romanos.</hi>
               </note>. And elſewhere the ſame author acknowledgeth, that <hi>this is the conſtant Doctrine of the Fathers, that a man cannot live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrina haec adco conſtans eſt apud patres ut paſſim affirment hominem non poſſe vivere ſinc peccatis,</hi> &amp;c. Eſtius <hi>ad.</hi> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 1.3.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewed you how contrary this opinion is to the Scripture; how contrary to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of beleevers; how contrary to the nature of grace and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and how contrary to the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38098:43"/>ſuffrage of antiquity; yea to the conceſſions of ſome of our Popiſh adverſaries.</p>
            <p>I need not ſpend time in anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cavils of thoſe, who aſſert, that perfection and abſolute free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from ſin is attainable in this life. There have been hints enough given already in the foregoing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to overthrow the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable of them. Should I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe about to anſwer them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, I muſt of neceſſity ſpeak over many of the ſame things again, which have been already delivered; but that I preſume will be a needleſs trouble both to you and to me. Therefore I forbear: One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I cannot but take a little notice of one Text of Scripture, upon which (though it be a pretious golden foundation) a late Author
<note n="b" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tho. Drayton</hi> late Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier of <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Wiles in his Book enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the Proviſo of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> hath built much hay and ſtubble. It is that of the Apoſtle in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Having therefor theſe promiſes, dearly beloved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filt hineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38098:43"/>holyneſs in the fear of God.</hi> From which words the aforeſaid Authour inferreth his Doctrine of perfection and freedome from ſin in this life. But, how little ſtrength or ſolidity there is in his inference, will eaſily appear. For his whole diſcourſe runneth upon a <hi>wrong ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and therefore the <hi>foundation</hi> being ſo feeble, the <hi>ſuperſtructure</hi> may caſely be overthrowne.</p>
            <p>Now the ſuppoſition, that he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon is this; <hi>that perfect cleanſing &amp;c. is made a condition of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> and hence he inferreth, that if <hi>abſolute freedome from ſin be not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineable, the condition of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is impoſſible, and</hi> conomine <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my beloved,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt his ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is falſe; for had the Apoſtle made perfect cleanſing, the <hi>condition</hi> of the promiſes, he would not have ſaid, <hi>having theſe promiſes,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>if ye would have theſe promiſes.</hi> The Apoſtle ſuppoſeth an intereſt in them, and from thence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth duty, not as a condition, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38098:44"/>obtain an intereſt in them, but as a fruit or expreſſion of our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs for an intereſt already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>Beſides,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Dato ſed non conceſſo,</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeing but not graunting, that perfect cleanſing is a condition of the promiſes, the inference is a meer <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> it doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that the condition of the promiſes is <hi>eo nomine</hi> unjuſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe impoſſible. For God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no more than once he beſtowed upon us; and we have loſt it through our own default. This perfect pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we had once in <hi>Adam, Eccl.</hi> 7.29. <hi>God made man upright, but he ſought out many inventions:</hi> and therefore <hi>our inability to obey</hi> doth not take away <hi>Gods authority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> God doth not loſe his <hi>right to command,</hi> though man hath loſt his <hi>power to obey.</hi> Our <hi>impotency</hi> doth not at all diſſolve our <hi>obligation.</hi> Perfect cleanſing is never the leſſe our duty, for our inability to attain it here.</p>
            <p>Again Gods commands are not
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:38098:44"/>meaſures of our ſtrength. We cannot draw a good argument, <hi>a mandato ad effectum,</hi> from what God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to what we can doe. <hi>Things are thus expreſſed</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>for another purpoſe, to ſhew Gods right, to convince the creature of weakneſſe, to ſhew us our duty, that mans endeavour is required, and that we ſhould doe our ut moſt, to convince us wherein we have failed,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="c" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> on <hi>James.</hi> p. 177.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But this may ſuffice to have been ſpoken to that uſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> The next uſe which I ſhall make of this point,
<note place="margin">Caution.</note> ſhall be an uſe of <hi>caution,</hi> and this uſe will concern both <hi>Sinners</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It may be applyed by way of <hi>Caution</hi> to <hi>ſinners</hi> to prevent the <hi>ill uſe</hi> they may make of this Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine:
<note place="margin">To ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> and there are two words of Cautionary advice, which I would ſpeak to them; the Lord alſo ſpeak, them home with power to their hearts, or elſe all that I ſhall ſpeak, will be in vaine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let them take heed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> how they imbolden themſelves to ſinne,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38098:45"/>by the falls of Saints, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let them take heed of inſulting over the Godly, becauſe of their failings. I begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauti.</hi> 1.</note> Let them take heed how they imbolden themſelves to ſin, by the falls of Saints recorded in the Scripture. It is an argument of a baſe ſpirit, for men to plead <hi>Noahs</hi> drunkenneſs, <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt, <hi>Davids</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, <hi>Peters</hi> denyall, as examples to encourage themſelves to ſinne. <hi>Salvian</hi> complaineth, that in his times they pleaded, <hi>Si David, cur non &amp; ego? Si Noah, cur non &amp; ego? If David committed adultery, why may not I doe ſo too, and yet beſaved as well as he? If Noah was drunk why may not I be ſo too, and yet be ſaved as well as he? The beſt, have their faults, and in many things we offend all.</hi> Thus they did <hi>then</hi> and thus men will <hi>ſtill</hi> ſtrengthen themſelves in their wickedneſs. But let ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons conſider.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They doe <hi>wreſt and pervert
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38098:45"/>the Scriptures</hi> when they make ſuch carnall inferences from the falls of Saints recorded therein; I ſay they pervert and wreſt the Scriptures to a quite contrary end, than ever the holy Ghoſt intended them.</p>
            <p>For there are but two ſpeciall ends of Gods recording in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the falls of his Saints: and they are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that their falls might be a meanes to preſerve others from fainting under the burden of their ſins, that they may not, when they fall, deſpair of mercy, or think their ſinnes greater than can be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that their falls may be warnings to others, to preſerve them from falling: that they may be as <hi>ſea-markes</hi> to warn others to take heed, how they come neer thoſe <hi>rocks</hi> and <hi>quickſands,</hi> where others have been <hi>ſplitt</hi> and <hi>ſunk;</hi> and to avoid thoſe <hi>ſnares,</hi> wherein the moſt precious Saints of God in former ages have been enſnared. Now <hi>theſe things are writen for our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38098:46"/>examples</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. Examples? How? Surely not for our <hi>imitation,</hi> but for our <hi>admonition,</hi> as <hi>verſe</hi> 11. to the intent, that we might not be ſurprized and overtaken with the like temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructionem, &amp; caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda ſunt.</hi> Eſtius. <hi>ad</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Vt iis lectis vel auditis admoniti ſapriamus, nè ſimiliter peccantes ſimiliter patiamur.</hi> Eſtius. <hi>ad</hi> verſe 11. <hi>ejuſdem capitis.</hi>
               </note>. This is the uſe which the holy Ghoſt teacheth us to make of the falls of Saints. And this uſe <hi>Nehemiah</hi> made of the ſin of <hi>Solomon</hi> in marrying ſtrange wives. You may ſee his own words, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.26, 27. <hi>Did not Solomon King of Iſrael ſin by theſe things? yet among many nations was their no King like him, who was beloved of his God, and God made him King over all Iſrael; Nevertheleſſe, even him, did outlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh women cauſe to ſin. Shall we then hearken unto you, to doe all this great evill, to tranſgreſſe againſt our God in marrying ſtrange wives?</hi> q.d. If <hi>Solomons</hi> marrying of ſtrange wives was a meanes to cauſe him to ſin, how much greater cauſe have we to fear the like effect of the like ſin, if we ſhould fall into it? Let us then make this uſe of the falls
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38098:46"/>of Saints recorded in the Scripture. Was ſuch a man as <hi>Noah,</hi> of whom the holy Ghoſt gives a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable teſtimony, that he was <hi>a juſt man and perfect in his generation,</hi> Gen. 6.9. overtaken with that beaſtly ſin of drunkenneſs? Was ſuch a man as <hi>David, a man after Gods own heart</hi> drawn to ſuch foule ſins as adultery and murder? Did <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>meekeſt man upon the earth</hi> breake forth into paſſion, and ſpeak ſo <hi>unadviſedly</hi> with his lips, that he was ſhut out of <hi>Canaan</hi> for it? Oh! how ſhould their examples be warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to us, who come ſo farre ſhort of them in grace, to take heed of the occaſions of the like ſins; and looke well to our own feet, leſt they alſo ſlip? Surely, it never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the heart of God to record the falls of his Saints, that thereby others, ſhould have a <hi>cloak</hi> for their ſins; but that hereby others might become the more <hi>afraid</hi> of ſin, and the more <hi>watchfull</hi> over their own hearts. Did <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and others, who were ſuch <hi>ſtrong</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:38098:47"/>Saints, and like <hi>pillars in the houſe of God,</hi> fall ſo dangerouſly? Oh! then how neerly doth it concern us, who ſtand in more <hi>ſlippery</hi> ground, to look well to our ſelves, and to take heed, leſt we alſo fall! Thus you ſee, they that take occaſion from the falls of Saints, which are upon record in the Scriptures, to encourage themſelves in ſin, doe groſſely pervert and wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and doe in effect make God the patron of ſin. Therefore I beſeech you take heed of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> You will ſee but little cauſe to imbolden your ſelves in ſin, by the examples of the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Saints recorded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture if you conſider how deeply they have ſmarted for thir ſins. It is true indeed, the Scriptures tell us that many of Gods deer children have <hi>ſinned fowlly;</hi> but they hold forth, that they have <hi>ſmarted deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Truly a man that conſiders, and layeth well to heart, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely God hath dealt, even with his own people, when they have
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38098:47"/>ſinned againſt him; what frownes, what hidings of Gods face, and what broken bones their ſins have coſt them; and how long ſome of them have roared upon the rack of Gods heavy diſpleaſure, before thoſe broken bones have been ſet in joint again; beſides many tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall afflictions which they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone, though not <hi>ſub ratione penae</hi> as the fruits of <hi>vindictive juſtice;</hi> yet <hi>as the effects of fatherly diſpleaſure.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Deus abſolvit vere peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes propter Chriſti mortem, ab omni pen a ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ, non ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men illos liberat ab omni penâ medicinali &amp; caſtlig<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriâ.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren <hi>in Coloſſ. ed it. Camah.</hi> 1639. p. 127.</note>: would be loath to purchaſe the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or the profit of any ſin at ſo dear a rate; much leſſe would he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden himſelf to ſin by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Though it be true indeed that God never <hi>taketh away his lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs from his people, nor ſuffers his faithfulneſse to fail,</hi> Pſal. 89.33. <hi>yet if his covenant-people forſake his Law, and walk not in his judgments; if they break his ſtatutes, and keep not his commandements; then will he viſit their tranſgreſſion with the rod, and their iniquity with ſtripes,</hi> verſe 30.31.32. The Scripture aboundeth with inſtances of this. <hi>Moſes</hi> his paſſion
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38098:48"/>and unbelief ſhut him out of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, Numb.</hi> 20.12. <hi>and</hi> 27.13, 14. And <hi>Davids</hi> Adultery and murder intailed the ſword upon him and his family to all generations; and the child born in adultery muſt not live, but dye, and that for this very cauſe, <hi>becauſe by this deed he had given occaſion to the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme.</hi> That's the cauſe alledged by God himſelf, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10, 11, 12, 14. And <hi>Zacharias</hi> for his unbeleef was ſtruck dumb for a ſeaſon, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.20. even <hi>becauſe he beleeved not the words of the Angel, which were to be fullfiled in their ſeaſon.</hi> Methinkes this conſideration ſhould ſtartle ſuch carnall wretches and cauſe them to <hi>ſtand in awe, and not ſin;</hi> that although the children of God are by Jeſus Chriſt <hi>delivered from the wrath to come;</hi> yet their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry infirmities have cauſed them to taſt deeply of the cup of Gods <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly diſpleaſure,</hi> and expoſed them and their familyes to ſore afflictions in this life, God thereby evidencing and declaring to the world his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38098:48"/>his hatred againſt ſin whereſoever he findeth it, and his faithfullneſs to his own people, in <hi>chaſtening them here, that they might not be condemned with the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.32.</p>
            <p>Now, friends, if you will be bold to partake of their <hi>ſins,</hi> it is juſt with God, that you ſhould alſo partake of their <hi>ſufferings.</hi> You may not promiſe your ſelves an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity</hi> from the like <hi>ſufferings,</hi> if you indulge to your ſelves <hi>a liberty</hi> to commit the like <hi>tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Scriptures alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord other things of the Saints, that are more worthy your imitation, than their ſins. You may read of of the <hi>meekneſſe</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as well as as of his <hi>paſſion,</hi> of the <hi>holyneſſe</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> as well as of his <hi>infirmities;</hi> the <hi>patience</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> as well as his <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience,</hi> in curſing his day: of the <hi>courage and boldneſſe</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> as well as of his <hi>cowardiſe</hi> in denying his maſter; in a word, you may read as well of the <hi>graces,</hi> as of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38098:49"/>the <hi>corruptions</hi> of Gods children. Surely, it would be your wiſdome to obſerve what is commendable in them, and rather to imitate them in their graces, than in their ſins; to obſerve what was excellent in them, and to make that a patern for your imitation.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauti.</hi> 2.</note> Let ſinners alſo take heed how they inſult over the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe of their fallings. If a profeſſour of religion doe but ſlip, how doth the world preſently condemne him for an hypocrite: and even while themſelves lye and wallow in ſin, and allow themſelves in all manner of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, how doe they inſult over the Saints for their failings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities? <q>
                  <hi>Theſe be your Puritans, your preciſians, your Holy Brethren, your Saints; they are all a company of hypocrites, and meer pretenders to Saintſhip,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now that you may ſee the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs hereof, Conſider</p>
            <p>Firſt; The Children of God are ſanctified but in part in this life.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38098:49"/>Though in regeneration the <hi>new creature</hi> be made partaker of the <hi>Divine nature;</hi> yet the <hi>Old man</hi> is not utterly aboliſhed. In converſion corruption is <hi>mortifyed,</hi> but not <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifyed;</hi> ſin is <hi>conquered,</hi> but not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.</hi> The children of God, when they become <hi>Saints,</hi> doe not ceaſe to be <hi>men;</hi> when they receive the <hi>Spirit,</hi> they doe not by and by wholly put off the <hi>fleſh;</hi> but the <hi>fleſh ſtill luſteth againſt the ſpirit,</hi> Gal. 5.17. and <hi>the law in their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers warreth againſt the law of their minds,</hi> and too often <hi>bringeth them into captivity to the law of ſin,</hi> Rom. 7.23. Therefore in inſulting over them for their failings, you ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and wrong the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods children
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.15.</note>.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If thou didſt reflect upon thy ſelfe, thou wouldeſt find more juſt cauſe to condemne thy ſelfe than them. Doth ſin <hi>dwell</hi> in them? why? it <hi>reignes</hi> in thee. Doe they ſin through <hi>weakneſſe?</hi> thou ſinneſt through <hi>willfullueſſe.</hi> Doe they ſin through <hi>infirmity?</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:38098:50"/>thou ſinneſt through <hi>preſumption.</hi> Are they ſometimes <hi>overtaken</hi> with a Temptation? thou many times go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forth to <hi>meet</hi> a temptation; and rather than fail, thou wilt turn De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and tempt thy ſelfe. <hi>Thou hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, doeſt thou judge thy Brother for the mote that is in his eye, when thou haſt a beam in thine own eye?</hi> Mat. 7.3. Surely if thou wer'ſt better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thine own heart, and was't thou not a ſtranger at home, thou wouldſt not be ſo buſy abroad.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Know this, that in judging the children of God thou condemneſt thy ſelfe. <hi>Thou art in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, oh man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt for wherein thou judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt another thou condemneſt thy ſelfe, for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame things,</hi> Rom. 2.1. In <hi>cenſuring</hi> thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>infirmities,</hi> thou doſt but <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate</hi> thine own <hi>impieties</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Turpe eſt Doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum.</note>. If his <hi>mote</hi> ſeem ſo big in thine eye, how great (thinkeſt thou) will thy <hi>beam</hi> appear in Gods eye another day? Aſſure thy ſelfe, that <hi>with what judgment thou judgeſt, thou ſhalt be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38098:50"/>judged; and with what meaſure thou meteſt, it ſhall be meaſured to thee againe,</hi> Mat. 7.2. and <hi>think not this oh man that judgeſt and condemneſt the people of God for their infirmities, and art thy ſelfe guilty of groſſe enormities that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2.3.</p>
            <p>Thus much by way of Caution to ſinners, to prevent the ill uſe, which they may make of this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This Doctrine may be alſo improved by way of Caution to Saints.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caution</hi> to Saints</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Let them take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of pride. If at any time your hearts begin to ſwell with pride, then minde your corruptions. When you begin to be exalted above meaſure by reaſon of ſtrength of parts, or eminency of grace, think upon your infirmities, and let this <hi>thorn in your fleſh</hi> prick the bladder of your pride. Surely the beſt of us have enough within us to pull down the pride of our hearts: when we are with the Peacock proud of our <hi>gay feathers,</hi> let us look upon our <hi>defiled feet,</hi> and be humbled. Alas? what have we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38098:51"/>to be proud of? We have nothing of our own but ſin. As for our gifts and graces, we may truly ſay of them, as the young man did of his hatchet, <hi>alas maſter, it was but borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.5.</note> Or in the words of the Apoſtle, what have I that I have not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and if I did receive it, why ſhould I boaſt, as if I had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it
<note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note>? When therefore the <hi>ſenſe of grace</hi> at any time <hi>lifts us up,</hi> let the <hi>ſenſe of corruption lay us low.</hi> Certainly there is more of <hi>ſin,</hi> than of <hi>grace;</hi> more of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> than of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> in the holyeſt man upon the face of the earth. As there are more <hi>weeds</hi> than <hi>flowers</hi> in the beſt <hi>garden,</hi> ſo there is more <hi>corruption</hi> than <hi>grace</hi> in the beſt <hi>ſoul:</hi> our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being <hi>ſtepmothers</hi> to grace, as the earth is to <hi>flowers;</hi> and <hi>naturall mothers</hi> to luſt, as the earth is to <hi>weeds;</hi> and the beſt men alive have cauſe to complain, that in them, that is, in their fleſh, there dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no good thing. And certainly let men be never ſo gracious, they have infinitely more matter of <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38098:51"/>through the abundance of corruption remaining in them, than of <hi>pride and exaltation,</hi> for the eminency or ſtrength of grace; there is more in their ſins to <hi>humble</hi> them, than in their graces to <hi>lift</hi> them up? eſpecially if we conſider theſe three things;</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The ſins of Saints are of the <hi>ſame nature</hi> with the ſins of wicked men. What though ſin doth not <hi>raign</hi> in Saints? It <hi>remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> in them ſtill; and is it ever the leſſe ſin, becauſe it doth not raign? Certainly there is the ſame <hi>violation of Gods</hi> Law, the ſame <hi>contrariety</hi> to Gods holy and Heavenly nature, the ſame <hi>diſobedience</hi> to the will of God, in the ſins of Saints, as in the ſins of other men. As a man cannot give the greateſt ſin a worſe, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he give the leaſt a better name, than ſin. I know no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at all in nature between the ſins of the Godly and the wicked; there is indeed a difference in their perſons, the one is regenerate the other unregenerate; but ſin is ſin
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38098:52"/>ſtill in both; though it raign in the one and not in the other. Surely this is a very humbling conſideration to the people of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſins of Saints, as they are of the <hi>ſame nature,</hi> ſo they are of the <hi>ſame deſert</hi> with the ſins of wicked men. All ſin is in its own nature damning; and that ſin doth not prove damning to the Saints, is (as one obſerveth
<note n="k" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Tho. Caſe Elias</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the Saints. p. 107. 108.</note>) not from the ſinfullneſs of their ſin, but from the greatneſs of Gods mercy not from the nature of their ſin, but from the goodneſs of Gods nature. And ſhould not this be matter of deep humiliation to the Saints of God?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Conſider yet further, that that their ſins, are in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>more hainous</hi> than the ſins of other men, and that upona five-fold account.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God is more diſhonoured by their ſins, than by the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. It is a greater diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the maſter of a family, if thoſe of his own houſehold walk
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38098:52"/>diſorderly, than if thoſe that are ſtrangers, or have no relation to him, walk diſorderly: So, in regard of the neer relation, that is between God and his people, their ſins re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound more to Gods diſhonour than the ſins of thoſe, that are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Religion ſuffereth more reproach by their ſins, than by the ſins of other men. The mouthes of the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> are thereby opened to reproach the wayes of God. Sins of profeſſours will be caſt as dirt upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion it ſelfe
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecce quales ſunt qui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum colunt. Salvian. de guhern. dei. lib.</hi> 4.</note>. Profeſſours are in the <hi>higheſt orb</hi> in the Church, and if their motion be <hi>irregular</hi> it is much noted. How ſad is it, that wicked men ſhould make a rod of the ſinnes of Saints to laſh Religion with?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There is more <hi>unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in the ſins of Saints, than in the ſins of other men. Hence it is, that their ſins are ſaid to <hi>grieve the Holy Spirit of God</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Res eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licata ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Dei. Tret.</hi>
               </note>. It goes neerer the heart of God, when his people
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38098:53"/>ſin againſt him, than when other men ſin againſt him. The ſinnes of others <hi>provoke God to anger,</hi> but the ſins of ſaints doe <hi>grieve his ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> Gracious ſpirit. p. 186.</note>. Siants are the objects of Gods ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all love, and therefore it muſt needs be grevious to the Spirit of God, that they ſhould offend him. The more a man loves a wife, or a child, or a friend; the more doth he take any unkindneſs from them to heart. So when Gods own people offend, it goeth neerer his heart, than when others offend; for there is more <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs</hi> in their ſins. Sins in Gods people are far more irkſome, and grievous to his Spirit, than ſins in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.30. <hi>The Children of Iſrael and the Children of Judah have</hi> onely <hi>done evill before me from their youth,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> read it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they <hi>alone,</hi> or they <hi>onely</hi> have been ſinners before me; as if God did not take notice of the ſins of other Nations
<note n="o" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Manton</hi> on <hi>James</hi> p. 150.</note>. <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods portion, whom he had <hi>avouched to be his people,</hi> are the <hi>onely</hi> ſinners Indeed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38098:53"/>a wound is deeper, by how much the neerer the hand is, that ſtrikes it. What thou my ſonne
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>? ſaid <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Brutus,</hi> when he ſaw his hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt ſtretched forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. By how much the more <hi>kindneſſe</hi> men ſin againſt, by ſo much the more <hi>unkindneſſe</hi> there is in their ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12. <hi>David</hi> complaineth, <hi>It was not an enemy, that had done this, but it was thou, my friend, and my equall, and my compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The friend wounded more than the ſword. To ſin againſt kindneſs is the greateſt unkindneſs. What <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſaid to <hi>Huſhai,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17. the ſame may God ſay to a ſinning Saint. <hi>Is this thy kindneſſe to thy friend?</hi> This ſhould be a ſoul-humbling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to the people of God, that every ſin they committ, is an unkindneſſe done to a kind God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> there is more unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs in their ſins, than in the ſins of other men. For they are Gods covenant-people, the vowes of God are upon them; they have given themſelves up to God in Covenant,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38098:54"/>and God expects better things from them. God ſpeakes confidently concerning them, <hi>Surely they are my people, Children that will not lye,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 63.8. God confideth in them; and therefore for them to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, for his Covenant-people to <hi>forſake his Law, and break his Commandements, this muſt needs be very hainous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Saints are advanced to a more excellent ſtate than others are: and this aggravates their ſins, and makes them exceeding and above meaſure ſinfull. God hath a ſpeciall intereſt in them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Exo.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.19.</note> they are his <hi>peculiar people, his peculiar treaſure above all people in the world;</hi> and therefore their ſins muſt needs be much more hainous than the ſins of other men. Hence God complaineth of the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking of his ſonns and daughters,</hi> Deut. 32.19. A late eminent Divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth ſins in the people of God to <hi>a ſtain in a piece of Cambrick or Lawn</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> on <hi>Hoſeah.</hi> vol 2. p. 179.</note>, which are eaſily ſeen. Indeed wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are (if I may ſo ſpeak) of a courſer threed, <hi>their heart is little
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38098:54"/>worth,</hi> and therefore, though they are ſullyed or defiled, that is not much taken notice of: even as a <hi>ſpot</hi> in a piece of <hi>ſackcloth</hi> is not ſo much obſerved, as a <hi>ſtain</hi> in a piece of <hi>fine linen.</hi> But now, the Godly are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed after the image of God, and therefore a ſpot in them is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bad. And thus you ſee, in many reſpects ſins in Saints are more hainous, than ſins in other men. Let theſe conſiderations take you off from pride, and cauſe you to walk humbly with your God. And ſo much for the firſt word of Caution to Saints.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cauti. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall give you the ſecond in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let them that ſtand take heed leſt they fall,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.12. and to that purpoſe, in order to their preſervation from falling, let them be perſwaded to follow theſe Directions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let them be watchfull.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dircti. </seg>1</label> Beloved, we know not whither our corrupt hearts may carry us before we dye. Let us not therefore be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; we have natures, that may
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38098:55"/>prompt us to the fouleſt ſins, that ever were commited. <hi>Peter</hi> was not jealous enough of his own heart when he told Chriſt, <hi>Though all men forſake the, yet I will not;</hi> nay he went further yet, and promiſeth, <hi>Though I dye with thee, I will not deny thee,</hi> Mat. 26.33, 25. and yet <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> did both; he both forſook him, and denyed him, and that with a curſe and an Oath, <hi>verſe</hi> 70, 72, 74. Had <hi>Peter</hi> known his own heart better, he would have been leſſe confident. Truly good men doe not know whither the corruption of their hearts may hurry them before they dye; nor with what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous violence they may be drawn to ſin, ſhould God leave them to themſelves. Chriſt therefore fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warneth his Diſciples <hi>Luk.</hi> 21 34. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting and drunkenneſſe, and the cares of this life,</hi> &amp;c, One would think this a ſtrange exhortation, and an uſeleſſe caution to ſuch good men as they were. Yet our Saviour
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38098:55"/>knew, that they had the ſeeds of thoſe ſins in their natures, which he forewarned them of; and the feeds of the ſame, yea of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſins are in our natures, as well as theirs; and therefore we had need take heed of ſecurity, and keep a jealous eye over our own hearts; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if we conſider, that ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity layes us open to temptation; and when we apprehend leaſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, our danger is greateſt. Sin and Sathan are ever watching their opportunity to doe us miſchief, and they have moſt advantage againſt us, when we are moſt ſecure: and at ſuch a time it is juſt with God to let ſin and Sathan looſe upon us, to affright us out of our ſecurity. If we are ſecure, we grieve the holy ſpirit of God, and tempt him to leave us to the temptations of the evill ſpirit; and the Devill watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for our ſlumbering, and lyes at catch for us, that he might take us napping. We are never more in danger to become a prey to this roaring and devouring Lion, than
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38098:56"/>while we lye ſleeping at his feet The Devill watcheth, that he might enſnare us; Oh! Let us keep an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch, leſt we be enſnared by him. The Devill keepeth a crafty and malicious watch, Oh! Let us keep an holy watch. Learn for ſhame, of the Devill, (ſaid holy <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>) to watch, ſeeing he is ſo watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Let us be awakened out of a <hi>ſleepy ſecurity,</hi> to a religious <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full jealouſies</hi> over our hearts; Let them, who thinke they ſtand, take heed leaſt they fall; as certainly they ſhall (though they ſeem to be pillars,) as <hi>Peter</hi> did, if they ſtand upon their own legs, and not upon his, that are as pillars of marble ſet upon ſockets of fine Gold, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>2</label> Let them carefully ſhunne the <hi>occaſions</hi> of ſin. It is true (I confeſſe) our ſinfull hearts would put us upon the commiſſion o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of ſin, if there were no occaſion preſented. But yet it is as true that occaſions doe ſtrengthen cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, as the Philoſopher
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38098:56"/>tell us that acts doe ſtrengthen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits. The occaſions of ſin doe (as it were) awaken corrupt nature. What elſe can be the reaſon, that a man, who did not think of ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, upon an occaſion perſented, ſhould preſently have a motion to commit it? Therefore be not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bold in ventureing upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſin. <hi>Thoſe that carry Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-natures about them, had need beware not onely of fiery darts, but of the leaſt ſparks</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> on <hi>Ja.</hi> p. 4. 69.</note>. Chriſt teacheth us to pray, <hi>Lead us not into Temptation</hi>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.13.</note>: Surely the way to be kept from temptation, is to keep at a diſtance from the occaſions of ſin. To pray, <hi>Lead us not into temptation,</hi> and then to ruſh upon the <hi>Occaſions</hi> of ſin is all one, as for a man to pray, that he may not be burn't, and as ſoon as he hath done, to thruſt his fingers into the fire. Surely we ſhall never overcome temptations, unleſſe we turn from the occaſions of ſin. A ſad examle of this we have record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Confeſ. lib.</hi> 6. cap. 8.</note>, of one <hi>Alipius,</hi> who was by the importunity of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38098:57"/>friends prevailed with to be preſent at the <hi>Gladiatory-games</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> but being there reſolved to keep his eyes faſt all the while, ſo that though he was preſent in body, yet he might be abſent in heart: but upon a great ſhout, that the people gave at the fall of one of the Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, he opened his eyes, and ſo became an approver of that blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and barbarous ſpectacle. Gods children are bound to <hi>abſtain from the appearance of evill.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.22. The <hi>Nazarites,</hi> that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to abſtain from wine, were alſo forbidden to touch the very husk of the grape. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.3, 4. And it is obſervable <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.16, 17. that God would not be called <hi>Baali,</hi> but <hi>Iſhi. Thou ſhalt call me Iſhi, and ſhalt call me no more Baali. For I will take away the name Baalim out of her mouth, and they ſhall no more be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered by their name.</hi> Why, what hurt was there in that word? Surely none at all in the word it ſelfe. The word is a very good word, and hath a very good ſignification, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38098:57"/>(as a late writer hath obſerved
<note n="u" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Jer. Burroughs</hi> in his Lectures on <hi>Hoſea</hi> p. 549.</note>) <hi>It is as proper to God, as any word that can be given him by the Church (but that God did forbid it here) for it is no more, when the Church calleth God Baali, than if the Church ſhould ſay, O God that art my Lord and my husband, who art to rule and govern me. Yea, and we doe find that God giveth himſelf this name,</hi> Eſ. 54.5. <hi>Thy maker is thy hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; the word that is rendered husband is in the Hebrew Baali.</hi> Why then is the uſe of the word to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? why, <hi>becauſe they had abuſed the word and given it to Idols</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>ibid</hi> p. 556.</note>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God promiſeth, that he would take away the name out of their mouthes, that they might have no occaſion of returning to Idolatry; That they might be kept from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, they muſt not ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the name of Idols So <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.13, 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not have in thy</hi> bag <hi>divers weights, a great and a ſmall. Thou ſhalt not have in thy</hi> houſe <hi>diverſe meaſures, a great and a ſmall.</hi> Why? may ſome ſay, was it ſuch a great matter for a man to have a great and a ſmall weight in his <hi>bag?</hi> and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38098:58"/>a great and a ſmall meaſure in his <hi>houſe?</hi> The thing in it ſelfe was not great, ſo they did not buy and ſell by theſe weights and meaſures. But therefore God forbids them, to have the one in their <hi>bag,</hi> the other in their <hi>houſe,</hi> leſt the having them there, ſhould prove a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, to bring them alſo into their <hi>ſcales,</hi> and into their <hi>ſhops</hi> to buy and ſell by them. God would have us keep off from the <hi>occaſions</hi> of ſin. The beſt way to prevent fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a <hi>Pit</hi> is to keep farre enough from it; ſo the beſt way to prevent falling into ſin is to keep farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from the occaſions of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>3</label> Let them look well to their <hi>company.</hi> Avoid intimate fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with ſuch, whoſe ſociety may corrupt you. Shunne ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, where you can expect no good, but may receive much hurt. <hi>David</hi> maketh this one cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Citizen of <hi>Zion,</hi> that <hi>in his eyes a vile perſon is contemned.</hi> Pſa. 15.4. <hi>Joſeph</hi> would not truſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the company of his miſtreſſe, leſt by her ſollicitations he might
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38098:58"/>be drawn to ſin; he <hi>hearkened not unto her to lye by her, or</hi> to be with her. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.20. Evill company is very infectious and dangerous, and therefore it is <hi>Solomons</hi> advice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.24.25. <hi>Make no friendſhip with an angry man, and with a furious man thou ſhalt not goe, leſt thou learn his wayes, and get a ſnare to thy ſoul:</hi> which words, although they are ſpoken of an <hi>angry</hi> man, yet they are true of all <hi>evill company</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. All ſinfull and unclean ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are <hi>infectious</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; either to <hi>diſſwade</hi> from that which is <hi>good,</hi> or to <hi>perſwade</hi> to that which is <hi>evill.</hi> Hence it is that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> warned the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to have nothing to doe with the Canaanites, leaſt they ſhould be miſled by their examples, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3, 4. And when they acted againſt this rule, they quickly brake all rules, as you may ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.35, 36. <hi>They were mingled with the Heathen,</hi> and then it immediately followeth, <hi>and learned their workes.</hi> What workes were theſe? Workes of <hi>art</hi> or <hi>agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture?</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:38098:59"/>of <hi>peace</hi> or <hi>warre?</hi> No ſuch matter, but they were workes of falſe worſhip and Idolatry, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the following words; <hi>They ſerved their Idols, which were a ſnare unto them.</hi> Therefore the Lord injoyned them to have no fellowſhip with them, leaſt they ſhould learn their wayes.</p>
            <p>Be perſweded therefore, to <hi>have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe.</hi> Eph. 5. and to induce you thereunto, conſider that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 13.20. <hi>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe, but a company of fooles ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>4</label> Let them look well to their <hi>ſenſes.</hi> As in a City beſieged, they look well to their <hi>Gates</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes;</hi> ſo Saints, if they would prevent ſin ſhould look to their <hi>ſenſes,</hi> which are (as it were) the <hi>Gates</hi> and <hi>Windowes</hi> of the ſoul; eſpecially to the eye, which <hi>affects,</hi> or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>infects</hi> the heart with ſinne, from ſinne-occaſioning Objects.</p>
            <p>It is therefore ſaid that <hi>Eve</hi> ſaw
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38098:59"/>
               <hi>that the fruit was faire, and to be deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and then ſhee did eat.</hi> Gen. 3.6. And as elſewhere <hi>The Sonnes of God</hi> ſaw <hi>the daughters of men, that they were faire, and took them wives.</hi> Gen. 6.2. And <hi>Tamar,</hi> when ſhee had a deſire to commit uncleanneſs with <hi>Judah ſat</hi> (as our tranſlation hath it) <hi>in an open place;</hi> but it is in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew <hi>in the doore of eyes:</hi> ſo called, becauſe it was ſuch a place, where ſhee might be ſo expoſed to open view
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, locoo patente ubi in omnes partes patet circumſpectio.</hi> Paraeus <hi>ad loc. Fuit bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium ubi neceſſe erat</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udam <hi>tranſire, undecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> veniret, Eâ igitur conſpectâ ille mox libidine accenditur meretricem ratus,</hi> Pareus <hi>ubi ſuprà.</hi>
               </note>, that <hi>Judah</hi> ſhould not paſſe that way, but he muſt of neceſſity ſee her, and ſeeing her, might be tempted to commit Inceſt with her.</p>
            <p>And it is ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.7. that <hi>Joſephs Miſtreſſe caſt her eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Joſeph, and ſaid lye with me.</hi> Her eyes infected her heart, and were the <hi>bellowes,</hi> that blew up
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38098:60"/>ſuch a flame of luſt within her
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Oculi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudici in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiunt cor, nunciantes ei objecta illicita, quae foris ſunt. &amp; borum ſpecie obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ illud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes; ubi cor eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum oculi porrò ſunt folles, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus illici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta cordis deſi deri a amplius ſufflantur.</hi> Paraeus <hi>ad Gen.</hi> 39.7.</note>. And you know, that one idle glance upon <hi>Bathſhebah</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Davids</hi> fall, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2, 3, 4. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids wandring eye</hi> uſhered in thoſe ſins, which afterwards coſt him <hi>broken bones.</hi> Hence we read of ſome, that had <hi>eyes full of adultery,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. A ſin which is in the eye, will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be at the heart; which cauſed <hi>Job</hi> to make a covenant with his eyes, that he might not look upon a maid, <hi>Job</hi> 31.1. He meanes, ſinfully to luſt after her. He knew that there is a ſpeedy and quick paſſage from the eye to the heart, though in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the body, there ſeemeth to be a great diſtance between them. Therefore (ſaith he,) I have made a covenant with mine eyes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void occaſions of ſin, leſt mine eye ſhould pollute my heart with moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto ſin. And upon this account <hi>David</hi> prayeth to God, that he would turn away his eyes from beholding vanity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.37.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>5</label> Obſerve the firſt riſings and ſtirrings of corruption, and reſiſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38098:60"/>them. Small breaches in a ſea-bank occaſions the ruine of the whole, if not timely diſcovered and repaired; ſo ſin will gain upon us by inſenſible degrees; and thoſe, that are once in the Devils ſnare, are ſoon taken by him at his will and pleaſure. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould therefore watch againſt the firſt riſings of ſin, and having diſcovered them, reſiſt them. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is no other meanes can doe you good, if this be neglected.</p>
            <p>There are but four wayes
<note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ralph Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon</hi> in his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly armed. p. 47.</note> can be imagined, whereby we may help our ſelves when we are aſſaulted with temptation; <hi>viz.</hi> either, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Firſt To flye; or 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Secondly To yeeld; or 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Thirdly To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound: or 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Fourthly To ſtand our ground, and make reſiſtance. Now none of all theſe, but the laſt will doe us any good.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is to no purpoſe to <hi>flye;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for ſin is an <hi>inteſtine</hi> enemy. As one ſaid of <hi>Solomon, that though he had no enemy abroad, yet he found one at home</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſtem foris non habbet, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi tamen reperit. Cun. de. rep. Heb. lib.</hi> 1.</note>; ſo it may be ſaid of us: though we had no enemy without
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38098:61"/>us, (which (ſuch is our miſery) cannot be ſaid of any of us) yet there are many noyſome luſts <hi>dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in us. which <hi>warre againſt the ſoul,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.11. and are active and ready to betray us to Sathan. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore can we flye, as long as there is an enemy within us, and will be within us, as long as we live, and follow us whitherſoever we goe?</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is to as little purpoſe to <hi>yeeld,</hi> that's the high way to ruine; for ſin, when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth death, <hi>James</hi> 1.15. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if you yeeld, you put your ſelves (as one hath well obſerved) out of the compaſſe of Chriſts pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<note n="c" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ralph Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon,</hi> in his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plertly armed. p. 47.48</note>. I have prayed for thee (ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Peter</hi>) that thy faith fail not <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32. Chriſt doth not make interceſſion for ſuch as yeeld, but for ſuch as reſiſt. He prayeth that the faith of ſuch as make reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſhould not fail, but he doth not intercede, that ſuch, as will not fight, ſhould be defended.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Compounding</hi> will ſtand
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38098:61"/>you in as little ſteed as either of the former. Luſt will never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, but to your infinite <hi>diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> if not to your <hi>deſtruction.</hi> The <hi>ſnares of ſin</hi> and Sathan will in the end prove <hi>chaines of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, It remaines therefore,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that it is your beſt way to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. As yeelding and compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the way to ruine, ſo <hi>reſiſting</hi> is the way to overcome. If you make a vigorous reſiſtance, Chriſt will help you to put your feet upon the necks of thoſe luſts, that <hi>warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſouls,</hi> and you ſhall be more than conquerours, through him that loved you and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for you.</p>
            <p>Now in reſiſting the riſings of of ſin, let me adviſe you to follow theſe rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Reſiſt <hi>ſpeedily.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Don't ſtay too long before you begin the fight. Many times men ſtay ſo long before they begin, that they are vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before they fight. Therefore reſiſt the firſt appearances of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38098:62"/>give no place to the leaſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; oppoſe ſin in the birth; cruſh the Cockatrice in the egge. It is eaſier to <hi>keep an enemy out</hi> of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, than to <hi>beat him out,</hi> when once he is gotten in: ſo it is eaſier to keep out ſin, than to beat it out. Dangerous diſeaſes may be ſtopped in time, which will afterwards prove incurable
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is obſta; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na paratur, Cum mala per longas invaluere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moras.</hi> Ovid.</note>. Sin, if it be timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, may probably prove no more dangerous to us, than the Viper proved to <hi>Paules</hi> hand, when he ſhook it off into the fire, and it did him no harme
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 28.5.</note>. But if we give way to it, and doe not reſiſt it in the firſt motion, it will be hard for us to ſuppreſſe it afterwards.</p>
            <p>Doe you therefore to your ſins as <hi>Pharoah</hi> gave command to be done to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> male-children: he would not ſtay till the children were grown up to years, but commanded the Midwives to ſlay them as ſoon as they were born. This was a <hi>cruell</hi> act in him; but thus to deal with your ſins will be a <hi>mercifull</hi> act in you to your ſouls. What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38098:62"/>
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did <hi>cruelly</hi> againſt thoſe poor children, doe you <hi>prudently</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſins; kill them, when they are in the birth. That's the firſt rule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let your reſiſtance be <hi>univerſall,</hi> you muſt reſiſt all ſin,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>every falſe way.</hi> You muſt combate with all, though you can conquer none, as you ſhould and would. True hatred is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, againſt the whole kinde. You ſhould not therefore, while you frown upon one ſin, ſmile upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and while you thruſt ſome out of doors, hug others in your boſome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Enter not into a parly or treaty withſin;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but maintain the conflict. Sin is ſuch an enemy, that you muſt either kill or be killed. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict is of ſuch a nature, that there ſhould not be a treaty of peace, nor a ceſſation of armes all your life long
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Reſiſt in the ſtrength of Chriſt.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Goe not forth in your own ſtrength, but in the ſtrength of the Lord, and the power of his mights
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.10.</note>. Fetch in divin ſtrength and aſſiſtance; act faith upon the death of Chriſt, for the killing of ſin in you; and by prayer
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38098:63"/>call in divine helpe. So much for the fifth direction, obſerve the firſt riſing and ſtirrings of corruption and reſiſt them.</p>
            <p>Sixtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>6</label> Poſſeſſe your hearts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with apprehenſions of Gods Preſence, and <hi>ſet the Lord alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and walke as in his ſight.</hi> It was the grave advice of a Philoſopher to his friend
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> to his friend <hi>Lucilius.</hi>
               </note>, that he ſhould alwayes imagine, ſome ſevere <hi>Cato,</hi> or ſome other perſon eminent for vertue, to be alwayes preſent with him as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer and cenſurers of all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that hereby he might be keept within compaſſe, and reſtrained from vice. And indeed there is much in the eyes of men, to keep men from breaking forth into ſin; yea the ſatyriſt tells us
<note n="i" place="margin">Juvenal.</note>, that <hi>Maxima debetur pueris reverentia</hi>— a man would not commit a groſſe ſin in the preſence of a child. Is not then the pierceing and all-ſeeing eye of a ſin-revenging God much more ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to lay a reſtraint upon your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and to cauſe you to <hi>ſtand in awe, and not to, ſin?</hi> Certainly this would
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38098:63"/>be a notable meanes to preſerve you from breaking forth into ſinfull practiſes, did you but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that all ſins are committed in the preſence of a ſin-revenging God, who is able to look the ſoul of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner into Hell, with the <hi>rebuke of his countenance</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.16.</note>.</p>
            <p>Seventhly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>7</label> Labour to poſſeſſe your hearts alwayes with the feare of God; I mean, not a ſervile, but a filial feare of God. This hath a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full influence upon the heart, to preſerve it from <hi>backsliding,</hi> as may be gathered from <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.4. where you have a promiſe in theſe words, <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Hence that precept, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Stand in awe, and ſin not.</hi> Indeed this holy fear of God is as a <hi>golden bridle</hi> to the ſoul, when it would runne out to any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. It is like <hi>banks to the ſea,</hi> which keepeth in therageing waves of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, when they would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow all. And therefore in ſcripture you have theſe two put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>fearing God, and eſchewing evill,</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:38098:64"/>Job 1.1, 8. Yea, you ſhall finde that <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing evil</hi> is not only put as an <hi>effect</hi> of the fear of God, but it is put into the <hi>definition</hi> it ſelfe of the fear of God; <hi>the fear of the Lord is to hate evill,</hi> Pr. 8.13.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>8</label> Look up to Jeſus Chriſt with faith flameing out in prayer. His eye is wakefull enough, and his arme powerfull enough to preſerve you. There is a ſpring of <hi>ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt. Therefore when you have the greateſt ſtrength of grace in your ſelves, yet look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your ſelves unto Chriſt, and ſay ſtill as <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> did, when he had that great ſtrength of men, <hi>viz.</hi> an army 500000 ſtrong, <hi>Lord, we know not what to doe, onely our eyes are unto thee,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.12. And then, be your temptations never ſo violent, your corruptions <hi>never</hi> ſo ſtrong, yet remember, what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee;</hi> ſufficient to ſubdue thy corruptions, ſufficient to ſecure thy heart againſt the volence of Sathans temptations. Therefore look up to Chriſt; commit your way unto
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38098:64"/>him, and watch and pray, that you enter not into temptation
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41.</note>. So much for the uſe of Caution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> I come now to an uſe of <hi>exhortation.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exhor. </seg>
               </label> Is this ſo that the beſt of men are not ſo freed from ſin in this life, but that in many things they offend all? then ſuffer a few words of exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Bleſſe God that you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from a <hi>ſinfull ſtate.</hi> Never look back upon <hi>Sodom,</hi> but with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, and bleſſe God that you are eſcaped; and be thankfull to the Lord, who hath given you coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in your reines
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.7.</note>. You might have remained under the raign and dominion of ſin, and have gone on after the counſels of your own hearts to this day, had not the Lord graciouſly turned you out of that way. Oh! belſſe God, that hath overpowered your ſouls, and made you willing in the day of his power, to forſake your ſinfull wayes, ſo that although ſin <hi>dwells</hi> in you, yet it <hi>raignes</hi> not as in times paſt. Oh! bleſſe God that hath given you
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38098:65"/>counſell, and cauſed you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand aright. Certainly, this is no other but a beam of divine light darted into your ſouls; certainly this is no other, than a voice from Heaven that hath ſaid unto you, <hi>This is the way, walk ye in it</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Be exhorted to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the juſtifying grace of God, by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt. When the Apoſtle had in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> at large complained of the remainders of ſin in him, of the <hi>Law in his members, that warred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law in his minde; after he had cryed out, oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death?</hi> verſe 24. then he is preſently rapt up in admiration of the juſtifying grace of God by the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> verſe. 25. and then chap. 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 1. he maketh that triumphant concluſion, <hi>There is therefore now no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> A worthy divine now
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38098:65"/>alive
<note n="n" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwine</hi> in his try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of a Chriſtians growth, p. 47.</note> in a treatiſe by him publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, obſerves an Emphaſis in that little word <hi>[now,] mark</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that word [now,] that [now] after ſuch bloudy wounds and gaſhes, there ſhould yet be no condemnation, this exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalts this grace: for if ever, thought he I was in danger of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was upon the riſeing and rebelling of theſe my corruptions, which, when they had carryed me ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive, I might well have expected the ſentence of condemnation to have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but I finde, ſaith he, that God ſtill pardones me, and accepts me, as much as ever, upon my returning to him; and therefore doe proclaim with wonder to all the world, that Gods juſtifying grace in Chriſt is exceeding large and rich.</hi> Thus farre the aforeſaid Author.</p>
            <p>My beloved, this muſt needs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the juſtifying grace of Chriſt, that where there is ſo much matter of condemnation, there ſhould not be condemnation it ſelfe; that not onely all the ſins of the elect of God before converſion are pardoned, but ſins after regeneration; and though
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38098:66"/>we run upon new ſcores every day, yet theſe ſhould be ſtill paid, and that there ſhould be riches of grace enough, and merit enough to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don us, this exceedingly advanceth the juſtifying grace of God, and the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Bleſſe God for <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> grace. This is indeed a great wonder, that a childe of God ſhould have ſo much corruption left in him, and that that corruption ſhould not deſtroy grace, but that this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly plant ſhould thrive in the midſt of weeds; and this ſpark be kept alive in the midſt of a ſea of corruption. Our firſt parents had no ſinfull nature in them, and yet being tempted by the Devil they fell; but now, that beleevers, who have both a tempting Devil with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and a corrupt nature within, ſhould ſtand, and not fall away, this is the Lords doing, and it ſhould be marvelous in our eyes
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23.</note>. That we ſhould be kept by the mighty power of God through faith unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note>, that we ſhould have ſuch
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38098:66"/>ſtrong corruptions within us, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt our ſouls, and yet not be finally overcome by them, this magnifieth the eſtabliſhing grace of God. Grace cannot perſerve it ſelfe, of its felfe, in the midſt of ſo much corruption. We ſhould quickly turn bankrupts; and loſe not only degrees, of grace, but all grace, were it left in our own hands.</p>
            <p>But that corruption, that dwelleth in us, and our frequent falls, may teach us, that it is as as neceſſary, for God to afford us his preſerving grace, to continue what we had given us, as his preventing grace to give us what we had not. The <hi>body</hi> of ſin dwelling in us, may minde us, that it is <hi>by grace we ſtand;</hi> that were we left to our ſelves, we ſhould ſoon doe as our Father <hi>Adam</hi> did. There is naturally the ſame revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit in us, that there was in him, an <hi>aptneſſe and inclination of heart ready to depart away,</hi> Jer. 5.23. And we have the ſame enemy, the ſame tempter, to draw us away with the like temptations: and in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38098:67"/>thoſe, that are not preſerved by the mighty power of God, theſe things <hi>ſcil. corruption within,</hi> and <hi>temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without,</hi> doe prevail ſo farre, as to turn back many, who ſeemed to <hi>begin in the ſpirit,</hi> and to cauſe them to <hi>make an end in the fleſh</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3.</note>, and to <hi>return with the dog to his former vomit, and with the ſow, that is waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</note>. It is by grace we ſtand
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">2 <hi>Co.</hi> 1.24.</note>, and ſhould God but with draw the ſupply of his ſpirit and the inſtuences thereof from our ſouls, we ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious and liable to all aſſaults, not <hi>of fleſh and bloud, but of principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers, and ſpirituall wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neſses in high places,</hi> and open to all the furious attempts, and all the <hi>fiery darts of the wicked.</hi> Therefore bleſſe God for eſtabliſhing and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Bleſſe God for any <hi>diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments,</hi> that you meet withall in the wayes of ſin. Truly there is not a ſadder judgment in the world, than for God to ſuffer us to goe on in ſin without reſtraint; and it is as great a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38098:67"/>mercy, when God is pleaſed to lay ſtumbling blocks in our way, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in any courſe of ſin. It is promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a mercy to the Church, that ſhe ſhould meet with diſappointments in the wayes of ſin. <hi>She ſhall follow after her lovers but ſhall not overtake them, and ſhe ſhall ſeek them but ſhall not finde them,</hi> Hoſ. 2.7. As ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in ſin is a great judgment, whence that threatening, <hi>the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlider in heart ſhall be filled with his own wayes,</hi> Prov. 14.14. So diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment in ſin is a great mercy. We ſhould not therefore be troubl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but bleſſe God, when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have our wills. It is a mercy, when carnall deſires are diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Therefore God would have <hi>Abimelech</hi> acknowledge mercy in a reſtraint. <hi>I withheld thee from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt me, therefore ſuffered I thee not to touch her,</hi> Gen. 20.6. And <hi>David</hi> bleſſed God for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting his intended execution of his revenge againſt <hi>Naball,</hi> when he ſaid to <hi>Abigail; Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, which ſent thee this
<pb n="801" facs="tcp:38098:68"/>day to meet me; and bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou, which haſt kept me this day from coming to ſhed bloud, and from avenging my ſelfe with mine owne hand</hi> &amp;c. 1 Sam. 25.32, 33, 34.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let us every day labour for further degrees of <hi>mortification.</hi> Sin dwelleth in us, and it will dwell in us, while we live. Therefore what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother caſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31. <hi>I dye dayly;</hi> ſo let us in reſpect of our ſins <hi>dye dayly.</hi> Let us not look upon <hi>mortification,</hi> as the work of a day, or a moneth, or a yeare, but of our whole life time. Let us therefore continue our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours therein, and make a day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly progreſſe in this work, and every day labour to weaken the body of ſin more and more, praying againſt it, and watching againſt it, and ſtriveing againſt it in the ſtrength of Chriſt. So much for the uſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> I ſhall cloſe up all, with a few words of comfort to the people of God,
<note place="margin">Conſola.</note> who are apt to be caſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38098:68"/>down and diſquieted in their ſpirits by reaſon of the remainders of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in them, and their frequent falls into ſin.</p>
            <p>Beſides what hath been already ſpoken, in the explication of the Doctrine, that though ſin doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in beleevers in reſpect of its <hi>inherence,</hi> and its <hi>infectious nature,</hi> and its <hi>ſeduceing power;</hi> yet they are freed from it in reſpect of its <hi>domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, guilt, and condemning power;</hi> and beſides what hath been ſpoken before, concerning the difference between the <hi>infirmities</hi> of Saints, and the <hi>falls</hi> of wicked men, which may conduce much to the comfort of the people of God under their failings and infirmities; I ſhall now ſubjoyn three or four other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable conſiderations, with which I ſhall put a period to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Sin cannot ſeparate Saints from the love of God. If any thing in the world could quench and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the flame of Gods love to a beleeving ſoul, that which carries
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38098:69"/>in it the greateſt contrariety to Gods holy and heavenly nature muſt needs doe it; and that is ſin. But ſin cannot doe it. A <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore regeneration could not doe it; much leſſe ſhall an <hi>act</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> now you are in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> be able to effect it. For their is more malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in a <hi>ſtate of ſin,</hi> than in an <hi>act of ſin.</hi> Now (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>God commendeth his love to us; in that when we were yet ſinners, Chriſt dyed for us,</hi> Rom 5.8. If God love <hi>ſinners,</hi> while ſinners; then ſuerly his love to <hi>Saints</hi> cannot be broken off by ſin. If the time of their <hi>bloud</hi> was the time of his love, as <hi>Ezck.</hi> 16.6. then ſurely his love to them, when Saints is <hi>invincible, inviolable:</hi> he may (indeed) <hi>viſit their iniquities with ſtripes, and their tranſgreſſions with rods</hi> (it is a branch of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30, 31.) <hi>never the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe his loving kindneſſe will he not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly take from them, nor ſuffer his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſse to fail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God taketh notice of of, and accepteth that good, which
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38098:69"/>is in his Saints, notwithſtanding their ſins. Indeed men are apt ſo to minde their vices, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their vertues; a little evill makes men forget abundance of good. Men are apt to pitch onely upon the weakneſſes and failings of of the people of God, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look what is good in them; like <hi>flies,</hi> that pitch upon the <hi>ſore,</hi> and like <hi>vultures,</hi> that flye over the <hi>pleaſanteſt garden</hi> and pitch upon <hi>carrion;</hi> ſo wicked men <hi>watch</hi> for the <hi>haltings</hi> of Gods people, and feed their malice with their failings.</p>
            <p>But God takes notice of a <hi>little good</hi> in the midſt of <hi>abundance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill;</hi> of a <hi>little gold</hi> in the midſt of <hi>abundance of oare;</hi> of a <hi>little wheat</hi> in the midſt of <hi>abundance of chaffe.</hi> And it is worth our choiceſt obſervation, that when the Spirit of God in the Scripture giveth us the characters of Saints, he hideth their <hi>failings,</hi> and taketh notice onely of their <hi>graces.</hi> I will give you a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. If you look into Gen. 18.12. you ſhall find that <hi>Sarahs</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:38098:70"/>ſpeech was full of diſtruſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, <hi>ſhall</hi> I <hi>have pleaſure my Lord alſo being old?</hi> There was but one word, that of <hi>Lord,</hi> the note of <hi>rever ence</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> to her husband, and that the holy Ghoſt elſewhere taketh notice of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. <hi>ſhe called Abraham</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>And although <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times paſſionate; yet the holy Ghoſt ſtileth him the meekeſt man upon the face of the earth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Now the man Moſes was very meek, above all the men that were upon the face of the earth.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.31. There is no mention of <hi>Rahabs</hi> lye, but onely of her faith and peaceable behaviour towards the ſpies. <hi>David</hi> fell fearefully, and that more than once (as you have heard before) and yet you may ſee, what a character God gave of him; <hi>viz. that he kept his commandements, and followed the Lord with all his heart,</hi> &amp;c. 1 King. 14.8. <hi>Aſa</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo had his great imperfections, and yet when an account is given of his raigne, the holy Ghoſt giveth him
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38098:70"/>this high encomium, <hi>The heart of Aſa was perfect all his dayes.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. So <hi>Job,</hi> The holy Ghoſt ſaith concerning him, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 5.11 <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of Job.</hi> Yes, and we have heard of his <hi>impatience</hi> too in <hi>curſing his day</hi> Job 2. But this is not mentioned. <hi>Iob</hi> was <hi>patient for the main,</hi> though ſometimes the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of his ſuffering extorted from him ſome expreſſions of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. Indeed where the bent of the heart is right, the infirmities of Gods people are not mentioned. He that drew the picture of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> while he had a ſcarre in his face, painted him with his finger upon the ſcarre; ſo God is graciouſly pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put the finger of his mercy upon the ſcarres of his people. What a precious cordiall may this be, for the ſinking and fainting hearts of Gods children, mourning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſenſe of their corruption? Heoverlooketh what is theirs in them, and takes notice onely of what is his own; and when he comes to weigh them in the ballance
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38098:71"/>of the Sanctuary, he leaves out their corruptions, and puts nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſcales, but their graces. He hides his eyes from what is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and takes notice onely of what is good in them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Jeſus Chriſt, the High Prieſt of Saints, is now in heaven, at Gods right hand making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. Hence it is, that he is alſo called an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate,</hi> in that comfortable Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. <hi>If any man ſin, we have an advocate with the father even Jeſus Chriſt, the righteous.</hi> He is <hi>entered in within the veile</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb</hi> 6.19, 20.</note>, and there he appeares before God, and pleads the cauſes of his people, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his own merit unto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the merit of his death and paſſion, whereby he hath made <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> full ſatisfaction to divine Juſtice fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all their ſins. It is upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that the bloud of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid to <hi>ſpeake better things than th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloud of Abel
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24.</note>. Abels</hi> bloud plead<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt <hi>Cain</hi> crying for vengeanc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. <hi>The voice of thy brother
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38098:71"/>bloud cryeth unto me from the ground, to wit, for vengeance.</hi> It is as much as if the Lord had ſaid, although there be none elſe to accuſe thee, yet the innocent bloud of thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abel</hi> which thou haſt ſhed, doth ſpeak, yea cry aloud for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Etſi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num te ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſet, quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe cùm ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo tri ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leris fit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcius: tam<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n eſt qui te accuſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud me, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delicet itſe ſauguis fra tris tui, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocenter per te ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iſte, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis lo quitur co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram me, vindictam ſui à me tanquam juſto judice poſtulavi.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>in Gen.</hi> 4.10.</note>. But now the bloud of Chriſt hath a voice too, and that <hi>ſpeakes better things than the bloud of Abel.</hi> The bloud of Chriſt pleads for the Saints, crying not for vengeance, but for mercy and pardon for them
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non vindictam clamat, ſed veniam.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taeus <hi>ad loc. Sanguis</hi> Abel <hi>vindictam loquebatur,—Sanguis autem Chriſti melius loquitur quia veniam loquitur &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> Eſtius <hi>ad lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>, and by this meanes they are freed from the accuſation and condemnation of the Law, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto otherwiſe by reaſon of renewed tranſgreſſions, they doe every day, become obnoxious. And hence it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> throws down the gaunt-let (as it were) and maketh that triumphant challenge, <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that juſtifieth. Who is he that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38098:72"/>condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for us,</hi> Rom. 8.33, 34.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> There is a time approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not far off, when believers ſhall be freed from the very being of ſin. Here indeed in this life they are under a ſinfull neceſſity and ſin dwelleth in them and will dwell in them whether they will or no; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the pious ſoul, often cryes out with <hi>David, Woe is me that</hi> I <hi>dwell in Meſech, that</hi> I <hi>ſojourn in the tents of Kedar,</hi> Pſal. 120.5. How long ſhall I be peſtered with this troubleſome inmate? And with the Apoſtle, <hi>Oh wretched man that</hi> I <hi>am! who ſhall deliver me from this body of death,</hi> Rom. 7.24. But at death Saints ſhall be delivered from ſin. When the <hi>body of fleſh</hi> dieth, this <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death</hi> ſhall be quite deſtroyed. Corruption ſhall be then totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, <hi>when this mortall ſhall put on immortality, and this corruptible ſhall put on incorruption</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.53.</note> The Saints ſhall never after death be proud
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38098:72"/>more; nor grieve the Spirit of God more; nor have cauſe any more to complain of the hardneſs of their hearts, and the earthlineſs of their mindes, and the vanity of their thoughts. Their ſins may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them to death, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not proceed one ſtep further.</p>
            <p>It is with the people of God in this life, as it was with the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> they were delivered from their <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Taskmaſters, and that was a ſweet mercy to them; but preſently they ſee them at their heels, and upon their backs again, and this was exceeding bitter, and therefore the Lord to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them tells them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Thoſe Aegyptians, whom ye have ſeen to day, ye ſhall ſee them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain no more for ever.</hi> So that it is with the the children of God in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their ſins; they are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the bondage of their ſins; but yet their ſins may trouble them, and put them into frights, and raiſe in them many imbondageing thoughts of fear afterward; but
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38098:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet at death their deliverance ſhall be compleated, and then they may ſtand upon the ſhore of the other world, and ſee all theſe <hi>Aegyptians</hi> drowned in the red ſea of Chriſts bloud, and may ſay in the higheſt triumph and exultation of Spirit, concerning ſin and Sathan, and whatſoever elſe hath the face or deſerves to beare the name of a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Aegyptian; Theſe Aegyptians which we have ſeen and felt ſo often in the dayes of our mortality, we ſhall not feel, nor ſo much as ſee them again for ever.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what I have ſaid and the Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:38098:73"/>
            <head>Through the Authors abſence, many faults have eſcaped the Preſs. The ſmaller literall miſtakes and mispointings they indulgence (I hope) will pardon. Other more material miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, thou art deſired to correct with thy pen.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Errata.</label> PAge 1. line <hi>penult</hi> read <hi>Brethren.</hi> p. 3. l. 16. r. <hi>precedent.</hi> ib. l. 26. r. <hi>ſufficient.</hi> p. 5. l. 17. r. <hi>reaſons.</hi> p. 9. l. 21. r. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning.</hi> p. 10. l. 15. r. <hi>pardoning.</hi> p. 12. l. 4. r. <hi>Chriſts.</hi> ib. l. 26. r. <hi>Scripture.</hi> p. 14. l. 2. r. <hi>there.</hi> ib. l. 5. r. <hi>there.</hi> p. 15. l. 24, &amp; 25. r. <hi>finally.</hi> p. 16. l. 10. r <hi>inhaerens.</hi> p. 18. l. 15. r. <hi>into.</hi> p. 20. l. <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nult</hi> r <hi>wherein.</hi> p. 21. l. 22. dele <hi>alſo.</hi> p. 22. l. 9. r. <hi>permits.</hi> ib. l. 22 r. <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doundeth.</hi> p. 23. l. 24. r <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi> p. 24. l. <hi>antepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nult.</hi> r. <hi>as I.</hi> p. 15. l. 2. r. <hi>confident.</hi> p. 31. l. 13. r <hi>ſervants.</hi> p. 32. l. 20. r. <hi>luſts.</hi> p. 33. l. 13. r. <hi>imperious.</hi> ib. l. 18. r. <hi>heartily.</hi> l. 20. r. <hi>he.</hi> p. 34. l. 24. for <hi>after,</hi> r <hi>againſt</hi> p. 38. l. 3. r <hi>ſins.</hi> p. 41. l. 8. r. <hi>practiſes.</hi> p. 43. l. 3. r. <hi>fatigatus.</hi> p. 47 l. 4. dele <hi>us.</hi> ib. l. 6. r. <hi>abſolute</hi> l. 23. for <hi>Doct.</hi> r. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> p. 48. l. 22. r. <hi>there.</hi> p. 50. l. 16. r. <hi>faithfull.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b. l. 22. r. <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> p. 51. l 22. r. <hi>attainable.</hi> p. 58. l. 25. r <hi>therefore.</hi> p. 64. l. 15 r. <hi>there</hi> p 66 l 22. r <hi>dear</hi> p. 67. l. 10. r <hi>poenae</hi> p. 68. l. 16 r <hi>fullfilled</hi> p. 76. l. 12. r <hi>ſmallneſs.</hi> p. 78. l. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> r. <hi>Saints.</hi> ib. l. 7 r. <hi>grievous.</hi> p. 8<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 5. r. <hi>thee.</hi> p. 84. l. 12. r. <hi>jealouſie.</hi> p. 85. l. 6. <hi>preſented.</hi> l. <hi>antepenult.</hi> r. <hi>example.</hi> p. 86 l. 3. r. <hi>being there, reſolved.</hi> p. 90 l. 16. r. <hi>companion.</hi> p. 91. l. 3. d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le <hi>as.</hi> ib. l. 8 r <hi>ſate.</hi> p. 93. l. 2. r <hi>occaſion.</hi> p. 97. l. 25. r. <hi>might.</hi> ib l 26 r. <hi>divine</hi> p. 98 l. 14. r. <hi>overſcers.</hi> ib l. 16. r <hi>kept. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ult.</hi> dele <hi>comma.</hi> p. 100. l. <hi>antepenult.</hi> r. <hi>violence.</hi> p. 101. l. 22. r. <hi>bleſs.</hi> p. 110. l. 8. r <hi>there</hi> ib. l. 14. r <hi>ſurely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>In the margin.</label> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag. 6. r <hi>ſemirutâ.</hi> p. 12. r <hi>Newcomen</hi> p. 15. r. <hi>myſticall</hi> 16. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p 20. r <hi>concupiſcentiam.</hi> p. 32. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. il r. <hi>conſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etudo.</hi> p. 56. l <hi>penult.</hi> r <hi>ut</hi> p. 64. r. <hi>ſapiamus</hi> p. 67. r <hi>pae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tentes</hi> ib r <hi>poenâ.</hi> ib. r. <hi>caſtigatoriâ.</hi> ib. r. <hi>Daven.</hi> ib r. <hi>Cant</hi> p. 77. r <hi>Tert.</hi> p. 90. r <hi>loco.</hi> p. 93. r. <hi>hab. bat.</hi> p. 94 r. <hi>complea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
